<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Love in distress, or, The lucky discovery a novel / written by the honourable Lady ***</title>
            <author>Lady.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 181 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88603</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3210A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43698</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">42475108</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 42475108</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151240</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88603)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151240)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2251:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Love in distress, or, The lucky discovery a novel / written by the honourable Lady ***</title>
                  <author>Lady.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 132 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Onley, for H. Newman ..., S. Briscoe ..., and H. Nelme ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, and with print show-through; pp. 89-92 and 113-116 lacking. Best copy available for photographing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Newberry Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151240:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>LOVE in Diſtreſs: OR, THE Lucky Diſcovery.</p>
            <p>A NOVEL.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>The Honourable Lady</hi> ***</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>W. Onley,</hi> for <hi>H. Newman</hi> in the <hi>Poultry, S. Briſcoe</hi> in <hi>Covent Garden,</hi> and <hi>H. Nelme</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1697.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:151240:2"/>
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THere is now Publiſhed, Mr.</hi> Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis<hi>'s Miſcellany Poems, with ſeveral ſelect Tranſlations from</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>race, Juvenal, <hi>Mr.</hi> Boileau'<hi>s Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, Satyrs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and</hi> Aeſop<hi>'s Fables in Burleſque Verſe: To which is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, the Paſſion of</hi> Byblis; <hi>with ſome Critical Remarks on Mr.</hi> Oldham; <hi>with other Letters and Poems.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:151240:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To my Dear FLAVIA.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THAT Time I ſtole from my more Airy Diverſions, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to this little Piece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and tho my firſt deſign was not to have pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed it, nor ever deſired any Eyes to encounter it, but yours, and my own; yet for that Preſumption I lay it at your Feet, and beg your Protection, with a Charitable En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to Peruſe it with a partial Eye, and excuſe the firſt Sallies of ſo unworthy a Pen; yet were I ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable
<pb facs="tcp:151240:3"/>of producing the moſt deſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Volume in the Univerſe, I ſhould be Ambitious of no Nobler a Patroneſs: For it is not the ſound of a great many Titles that I covet, which, oftentimes like a hectoring Bully, makes a great Noiſe, with little or no Courage; not that I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe true Nobility, nor admire it farther then the Intrinſick Value.</p>
            <p>I have nothing to plead for the Meanneſs of the Preſent, nor any Reaſons for the many Objections you or any other may make, if you pleaſe to Criticiſe; only you have here the firſt Draught of ſometimes a Pleaſant, ſometimes a Hypocon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>driack Brain, without ever rectify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; yet my dear <hi>(Flavia)</hi> accept of this humble Offering from a Friend, and afford it the Reading; ſome leiſure Hour after the ſoft Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of your Lover's Sighs has been
<pb facs="tcp:151240:3"/>whiſpered to your Ears, and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally taught you, <hi>Love</hi> is not that Trifle to be ridicul'd at pleaſure, but rather the moſt ſerious Buſineſs of our Lives; nor imagine it too fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh a Subject to entertain you, but reflect on the Sallies of your own Heart, and after mature Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if you find that youthful Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom incapable of a tender Impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I will readily ſubmit to the moſt rigid Principle of the moroſeſt Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ick; but pardon my Opinion, if I believe it impoſſible, and dare con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently affirm, ſo much Vivacity, Wit, Fire, and Beauty cannot be incapable of an honourable Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: This is a ſort of Natural Philoſophy, at leaſt a Woman's Philoſophy, the only Theme they can Write of; and all theſe diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Paſſions are agitated by Love, Scorn, Jealouſie, Anger and Reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which if not diſplay'd in their
<pb facs="tcp:151240:4"/>true Colours, conſider the Author, and force a Complaiſance.</p>
            <p>I would avoid all things in the common Rode of Flattery, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhun a Character I could be very copious on, and only tell you, If this Trifle has but the Influence to effect a Smile from you, or the good Luck to diſperſe ſome melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly Cloud that would eclipſe the Luſtre of your Glorious Mind, I ſhall have the utmoſt of my Hopes, and eſteem my ſelf rewarded even to the height of my Laviſh Wiſh.</p>
            <p>I could ſay a great deal in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of Love, what Effects it has had over the profoundeſt Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, the moſt Judicious and Learned, even thoſe who have moſt contemned that Paſſion, have been delivered up to the moſt ſenſible Touch of it; bring authentick Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors
<pb facs="tcp:151240:4"/>to prove as much; produce the wonderful Effects of it in theſe Days; but that is not my part, I ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie nothing, but leave it to your Mercy; and if you do afford it your favourable Protection, I ſhall be proud I had the Occaſion to ſhew my Choice in a Perſon of ſuch ſingular Virtues, ſuch nice and refined Sentiments, ſuch ineſtimable Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and One whom ten thouſand Advantages, beſides that of Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, induces me ever to Subſcribe my ſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Devoted Friend, and Humble Servant, <hi>CORINNA.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:151240:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151240:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To</hi> CORINNA, <hi>on her Novel entituled,</hi> Love in Diſtreſs: <hi>or,</hi> The Lucky Diſcovery.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> Beg'd <hi>Apollo,</hi> that he would inſpire,</l>
               <l>For once, my Breaſt with ſuch Poetick fire,</l>
               <l>That I your Praiſe might to the World recite,</l>
               <l>And ſhow how much I value what you write:</l>
               <l>But the ill-natur'd God did Aid refuſe,</l>
               <l>Envious at Merit in a Female-Muſe.</l>
               <l>Spight of the Churle, boldly I'll pay a Mite,</l>
               <l>Tho' I expoſe myſelf by what I write.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Your Lines are ſtrong, ſo eaſy flows your Wit</l>
               <l>Your Verſe ſo ſmooth, your Sence is ſo polite,</l>
               <l>That you are ſure the Muſes Favourite.</l>
               <l>To what a wondrous pitch in time you'l grow,</l>
               <l>Who can ſuch Judgment on a Trifle ſhow!</l>
               <l>Trifles indeed to what your Mind poſſeſs;</l>
               <l>Proceed <hi>Corinna,</hi> and ne'r fear Succeſs.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>PHILANDER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:151240:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To my much-lov'd Siſter, Mrs. <hi>S. R. alias,</hi> my Siſter the Lady <hi>P.</hi> on her Novel entituled, <hi>Love in Diſtreſs:</hi> or, <hi>The Lucky Diſcovery.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>THus dare a Brother venture to commend</l>
            <l>Your firſt Attempt, and ſay 'tis nicely pen'd.</l>
            <l>Aſſiſt me then, ye Muſes, that I loſe</l>
            <l>Not one aſpiring Thought which I could chuſe.</l>
            <l>That I, inſpir'd by you, may add to Fame,</l>
            <l>And celebrate my dear <hi>Corinna</hi>'s Name.</l>
            <l>Well, could I give her Merit juſt Deſert,</l>
            <l>Could I expreſs the Dictates of my Heart,</l>
            <l>But 'tis impoſſible, not all your Aid</l>
            <l>Can ſpeak my Raptures of that Charming Maid.</l>
            <l>And, oh! I bluſh, that to my own Diſgrace</l>
            <l>I want Aſſiſtance for a Siſter's Praiſe;</l>
            <l>Yet I'll not wonder, 'tis her laviſh Store</l>
            <l>Has bankrupt mine, and render'd me ſo poor.</l>
            <l>Fain would I from a Character ſo true,</l>
            <l>So natural, and well diſplay'd by you,</l>
            <l>Give injur'd innocent <hi>Canace</hi> her Due.</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:151240:6"/>Deplore the deſperate <hi>Octavio</hi>'s Fate,</l>
            <l>Applaud that Turn of Fortune you relate,</l>
            <l>With ſo much Paſſion, Eloquence, and Wit,</l>
            <l>That whoe're reads muſt feel what you have writ,</l>
            <l>Let not one Character eſcape true Praiſe,</l>
            <l>And crown each lucky Thought with golden Bays:</l>
            <l>But, oh! in vain I've only the Deſire;</l>
            <l>For your bright Flame puts out my weaker Fire.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. R.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:151240:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To</hi> CORINNA, <hi>on her No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel entituled,</hi> Love in Diſtreſs: <hi>or,</hi> The Lucky Diſcovery.</head>
            <l>THe painted Grapes that drew the feather'd Train,</l>
            <l>Provok'd their hunger, but provok'd in vain:</l>
            <l>Advancing near, they ſoon perceiv'd the Cheat,</l>
            <l>And left, unſatisfied, the Fairy Treat.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Your</hi> lively Fancy does at once invite,</l>
            <l>And feaſt our raviſh'd Souls with true delight.</l>
            <l>Strange Art! that o're our Sence ſuch pow'r can gain,</l>
            <l>To make us feel thoſe Paſſions which you feign!</l>
            <l>Their Adoration baſely they miſplace,</l>
            <l>Who are enamour'd only on a Face;</l>
            <l>But conquer'd, and of Liberty bereft,</l>
            <l>Your Captives have at leaſt this Comfort left,</l>
            <l>That honourably vanquiſh'd, we ſubmit</l>
            <l>To double Charms of Beauty and of Wit:</l>
            <l>By theſe delightful Spells our Hearts are ſeiz'd,</l>
            <l>Fond of our Chains, and with our Ruin pleas'd.</l>
            <l>But when you dye, (as pity 'tis you muſt)</l>
            <l>Inſtead of mouldring into common Duſt,</l>
            <l>As a Reward for your ingenious Pen,</l>
            <l>The Muſes have decreed, <hi>Corinna</hi> then</l>
            <l>Shall mount to them, and make their number Ten.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>STREPHON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="novel">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151240:7"/>
            <head>LOVE in Diſtreſs: OR, THE LUCKY DISCOVERY.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>LIsbon,</hi> the principal City of <hi>Portugal,</hi> famous for its curious Traffick, and no leſs to be admired for the produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of Worthy and Brace Heroes; amongſt the reſt, a Noble Youth (whoſe Extraction was derived from the moſt Illuſtrious <hi>Seba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,</hi> the Nephew of <hi>John the Third,</hi> King of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Portugal,</hi> who was unfortunate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſlain in the Field of <hi>Alcazar</hi> in <hi>Affrick</hi>) and whoſe Royal Virtues, and Heroick Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, might worthily contain as many Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes as our <hi>Atlas:</hi> But rather than dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate in the leaſt from his acquired, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Fame, I will omit all Circumſtances of his Valour, and only recount the Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous part of his Life, with Impartiality.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:151240:8"/>His Parents injoyed all the Bleſſings of Peace, Honour, Wealth and Tranquility; all the Comforts that the World, or Nature can beſtow upon Mortals in this lower Sphere; yet nothing added more to their ſecret Satisfaction and Felicity, than the ſpringing Vertues, and Beauty of <hi>Melantius,</hi> which was the Name of this moſt Excellent Perſon. It was now he was attained to the Twenty third Year of his Age, and with that to all the Perfections, that a Soul ſtampt with the Image of a Deity, could be capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of: It was therefore no wonder if his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents were throughly ſenſible of his Deſerts, and knew how to ſet a conſiderable value on ſo ineſtimable a Jewel; they feared that his Generous and Ambitious Humour, would prompt him forward to be acting ſomething worthy of himſelf: And indeed he had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſolicited them to permit him to aſſiſt the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> againſt the increaſing Power of the Inſulting <hi>Turk.</hi> He pleaded the Juſtice of the Cauſe, the Shame of an Unprofitable Life; and, in ſhort, he told them, his Soul glow'd within him, to be attempting that which he had often envyed in other Brave Men; he urg'd that the Plenty of the World ought not to indulge a Man in Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; he had recourſe to the Emblem of the Bees, and their abhorrence of the ſlothful Drone: He omitted no Argument that might
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:151240:8"/>prevail; he feared no Danger, nor appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended Fate, but begg'd he might have leave to try his Fortune where Glory was to be gotten, and not like a Dunghil-weed rot at the Spot he grew.</p>
            <p>They heard, (and often bleſſed the Auſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Hour that gave him Birth) but never could be brought to condeſcend, that he ſhould launch for Fortune in the uncertain World: They told him, It was not the Juſt and Brave, that always reap the Benefit of their own Merits, for fickle Fortune is a Jilt, and often favours Fools and Knaves; yet found no Argument ſtrong enough to diminiſh in the leaſt, the aſpiring Spirit of this Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant Youth. At laſt they thought a Married Life the Infallible Remedy to ſecure the only Pledge of all their former Joys: He then found himſelf preſt to Marry, his Relations having propoſed to him a Match out of one of the Nobleſt Families in <hi>Portugal;</hi> her Name <hi>Aſpatia,</hi> only Child to the Duke <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonio de Almeyda,</hi> a Lady whoſe Perfections, ballanced with her Quality and Fortune, had made numerous Captives of leſs amorous Souls than our <hi>Melantius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was a ſhort Voyage down the famous River <hi>Tajo,</hi> that conducted him to the Scene of bliſs, firſt under pretence of a complemental Viſit; the Duke received him with an extraordinary and hearty Welcome, which
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151240:9"/>he return'd, by a grateful acknowledgment of his Favour.</p>
            <p>The Duke to divert his Noble Gueſt, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained him with a ſight of his magnificent Palace, where he took great delight in view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the unparallel'd Statues, and Paintings, and the curious Cielings, done by the moſt famous Maſters of the Age. After he had ſatisfied his Curioſity, as well as he could in ſo ſhort a time, the Duke led him into his Garden, which for the fine Scituation, and lovely Proſpect, the Orange, Lemon, and Citron-Trees, continually in Bloſſom, Fruit of all ſorts, and variety of all Flowers, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant ſhady Wilderneſſes, refreſhing and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificial Fountains; and, in ſhort, all that Nature or Art could render curious, made this exquiſit Spot of Ground be juſtly term<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Paradice of <hi>Portugal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their wandring Steps led them into a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired Walk, where <hi>Melantius</hi> was ſurprized with the ſight of a <hi>Beauty;</hi> and altho' the Jeſſamin-Hedges, which were very thick on each ſide, had eclipſed ſome part of her Charms; yet he had diſcovered ſo many Perfections, that he was reſolved to approach this unguarded Fair; who, if Heaven had informed, with a Soul agreeable to her Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, he had no farther thought, then an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire reſignation of himſelf: With theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templations he entred the Arbour, not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151240:9"/>by the Duke, who was juſt turn'd to gather a Flower, which gave him opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to gaze, as one void of ſence, upon this Lovely Fair. 'Twas at that Inſtant our young Enamourato's Thoughts were eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted beyond the Power of expreſſion.</p>
            <p>The Weather in thoſe Climates is violent hot, eſpecially that part of the Day, when the Sun is in the Center of the Zodiack; which ſo ſuffocates the Inhabitants, that they are willing to cloſe with all advantages, that can render a Refreſhment to their drooping Vitals: The ſame Motive induced this Charming Fair to receive the benefit of a ſoft ſtill Wind, that whiſpered Content through all the lazy Air. She had a Slave, whom ſhe was moſt ſecure in; but at this time ſhe had diſmiſſed her, that ſhe might with greater freedom enjoy the liberty of ſweet Contemplation: Love had been no ſtranger to her Heart, a Heart perhaps too apt to take the Impreſſion; and what Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the ſame Sex, that has ever experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented the leaſt Power of that Triumphant Tyrant, but muſt acknowledge, that altho' to feed their fancy, and divert their melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly hours; they may admit of a Confident, to treat with all advantage on the Object of their thoughts; yet there are ſome Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſports of Satisfaction, that cannot be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained under any limit, but breaks out into
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151240:10"/>Raptures; which when vaniſhed, dejected and ſurprized they even blame themſelves for being an Eye-witneſs.</p>
            <p>This place was all Retirement, ſecret and ſecure; none durſt approach except the Duke, at ſome appointed hours, wherein ſhe never failed to entertain her ſelf with all the privacy and freedom her Heart could wiſh: At this time her Soul, wrapt in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limer Meditations, had took its flight above all thought, and left the Body wholly bereft of ſenſe or motion; a profound Sleep ſealed her Eyes, and ſhe appeared as divinely charming to the raviſht <hi>Melantius,</hi> as the vertuous and excellent <hi>Lucretia</hi> did, expos'd a Victim to her audacious <hi>Roman</hi> Lover: A ſacred Silence ſeem'd to reign there, which ſecured her from all fears of Interruption, as in a Cave forſaken by wild Beaſts-in a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart.</p>
            <p>The ingenious contrivance of this Arbour rendred ſuch ſatisfaction to the ſight, that it unreſiſtably allured the Beholders to a ſolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry retreat; it conſiſted of four delicate little ſquare Beds of green Turf, on the fartheſt of which, lay this <hi>Amazing Beauty;</hi> her Head declining to the right ſide, ſupported by a Hand, that ſeemed to be form'd of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd Alablaſter, her Hair hanging careleſly mov'd at the diſcretion of a gentle Wind, the colour fair, compar'd to <hi>Cynthya</hi>'s Silver
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151240:10"/>Treſſes; ſhe had on a pair of embroyder'd Bodice, her Boſom half open, with a large white Damask-Scarf wrought with Gold, which falling off her Shoulders, had circled in her Knees, and likewiſe hid the other Arm, her Breaſt whiter than Snow, but of a warmer Conſtitution, wrought wonderful effects in a young tender Heart reſolved to love: The diſcovery of all theſe Charms, the powerful clearneſs of her delicate Complexion, was capable to make him ſurrender upon the firſt Aſſault.</p>
            <p>You muſt imagine the unavoidable ruſtling that he made, ſoon expiated the drowſie God, who gently ſlipt his Chain, and gave his Captive leave to open her bright Eyes; then with a Face more ſerene and lovely than <hi>Aurora,</hi> ſhe confirmed the languiſhing Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of her Amorous Lover; tho' the ſudden confuſion that ſeized every Faculty, at the approach of a Man, and a Stranger, diſperſed a pleaſing Bluſh throughout her Cheeks, and gave a raviſhing luſtre to her ſparkling Eyes, which were blue, and full of Life. With what new fire this kindled him is unaccountable; for never was Lover at the height of his Wiſh, ſtruck with a more acute Paſſion, than he was ſenſible of the firſt Minute; Fear, Pleaſure, and a reſenting Pity filled his Mind, to ſee her ſo ſeverely aſtoniſh'd, that ſometimes her Face with
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151240:11"/>Shame was glowing red, then ſtreight with Anger it grew pale.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Forgive me, Madam,</hi> (ſaid he, with an Air full of concern) <hi>by unadviſed ſteps, (tho' I must own 'twas not without deſign) I have incroached upon your Priviledges; charm'd with ten thouſand Beauties, inſenſibly I did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort to this Retirement. Sir,</hi> (reply'd <hi>Aſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> who had a little recover'd her ſelf) <hi>I pray, no more; call not more Bluſhes to my Cheeks; but if you will reſtore my Peace, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, and leave me to my innocent Retreat. Melantius,</hi> who could not brook this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, with eager Tranſport threw himſelf at her Feet, then bleſſed his happy Geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us which had been his Guide, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey'd him to the Shrine of Chaſte <hi>Diana,</hi> where he would offer up his pure Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>While thus he ſpoke, ſhe ſurvey'd him round, view'd and review'd his Noble Meen, obſerved his Speech, his Air, his Perſon, in all which diſcovered Worlds of Pleaſure. He was of a middle ſtature, well ſhap'd, the features of his Face were regular, black-ey'd, and languiſhing; his Hair was of a bright Aſh colour, which was very long, and lay in folding Curles all o'er his Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
            <p>With ſtrange amazement, and tranſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thoughts, they did for a great while
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151240:11"/>ſtand and gaze on one another. Then, then the little envious God of Love did clap his Wings, and rejoyced at the approaching Fate of theſe unhappy Lovers; but ſoon this pleaſing Extaſie was diverted by <hi>Aſpatia,</hi> whoſe Modeſty recalled her ſurpriſed Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits; then caſting down her Eyes which were filled with Shame, ſhe blam'd her moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudent Curioſity, when ſhe beheld <hi>Melantius</hi> Proſtrate at her Feet, with Eyes that ſpoke too open and intelligibly the Circumſtances of his Heart; yet forced a Smile to ſay, <hi>Indeed you are too obſequious, too laviſh of your Praiſe; and give me leave to impute theſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, to that common face of Gallantry, that generally attends your Sex, rather than to your ſolid Judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this time the Duke had recovered the Arbour; where he was ſurpriſed to find <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantius</hi> in a cloſe Converſation with his Daughter, who appeared in great confuſion; the Duke blamed his own Imprudence, in leading him that way, and as he entred the Arbour, excuſed himſelf, by telling her the agreeable Entertainment of that young Lord's Converſation, had wholly taken up his Conſideration; therefore to compence for having interrupted her accuſtomed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat, (which he attributed altogether to himſelf) they would leave her to her free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and ſeeing <hi>Laura</hi> the Slave of fair
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151240:12"/>
               <hi>Aſpatia</hi> appear, the Duke thought fit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire.</p>
            <p>This ſudden motion was ſomething per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexing to <hi>Melantius,</hi> who could not depart without a great Regret, which he ſignified by his Looks, which were all Remorſe. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately <hi>Aſpatia</hi> withdrew to her Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, where, as ſoon as ſhe enter'd, ſhe threw her ſelf careleſly on a Couch, and there ſat very dull and penſive; <hi>Laura</hi> ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining it no other, but ſome little concern for the diſorder ſhe was ſurprized with in the Garden; approach'd her with a pleaſing Look: <hi>Come, Madam,</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>baniſh this trifling Sorrow, here is that will make you ſoon aſſume your uſual Gaiety; a Letter from the Count</hi> Octavio, <hi>Madam. From</hi> Octavio! (ſaid ſhe, ſtarting in a little diſorder) <hi>Give it me. But what means my foreboding Heart? Can any thing from that brave Man diſpleaſe me? And yet I feel an unuſual Shivering over all my Limbs, as ſome dire Omen of a future Misfortune!</hi> She took the Letter with <hi>her trembling Hands,</hi> and having opened it, ſhe Read as follows.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:151240:12"/>
                  <head>OCTAVIO <hi>to</hi> ASPATIA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> ſee</hi> (dear Madam) <hi>how much I am yours, when even the Commands of my Prince, cannot detain me in</hi> Italy; <hi>nor the Threats of a Father induce me to Marry a Lady, whoſe Beauty has no Superiour but fair</hi> Aſpatia<hi>'s. I am the ſame conſtant Man, as when I left you, and only live to Adore you. What will my Fate produce? Cannot all my Sufferings, and the Sincerity wherewith I ſerve you, render me the most paſſionate of Lovers? Nor is it poſſible to reconcile the Duke, your Father, to a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger? Yet this is leſs my Care, then how I ſtand in the favourable Sentiments of the only Perſon I live by. I am now at</hi> Porto <hi>with all the Privacy imaginable, till I know with what Incouragement I may come to</hi> Lisbon. <hi>I ſhall wait with much impatience, to ſee the Characters of that fair Hand, from whom depends, the Life, Fortune, and Felicity of,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Madam, Your Unchangeable</hi> Octavio.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:151240:13"/>During the peruſal of this Letter, the Commotions of her Mind was viſible in her Face; and having concluded it, ſhe fetch'd a deep ſigh, and return'd to her penſive po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture. After ſome time lifting up her trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled Eyes, ſhe cry'd, <hi>Ah!</hi> Laura, <hi>did I Love</hi> Octavio? <hi>Laura</hi> ſmil'd at the oddneſs of the Queſtion, and made no Anſwer; whilſt ſhe continu'd; <hi>Was I not obliged in honour to make ſome return to him I owe my Life to? Nay more, the Life of him that gave me mine. But ſay I did advance too fast, too tenderly, forgive my Indiſcretion, it was no more than Gratitude did prompt me to: But why theſe ſcruplous Thoughts? Am I not the ſame</hi> Aſpatia, <hi>young, f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee, and diſingag'd? No, no, but he is ſtill the Brave the Generous</hi> Octavio; <hi>and must not, cannot, will not be impoſed upon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tormented with a thouſand different Thoughts, ſhe paſt the reſidue of the Day till Bed-time. <hi>Laura</hi> wondering much from whence this ſhould proceed, (tho' it requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red no penetrating Eye to diſcry a deep im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the Lovely Stranger ſtampt upon her Boſom) had uſed the moſt prevalent of her Arguments, to diſſwade her from that melancholy Humour: But alas! 'twas all in vain; ſhe retired to her Bed, where her Pillow was the only Confident to the Agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſhe ſuffered that Night; which was
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151240:13"/>ſpent with much more ſatisfactory Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by <hi>Melantius,</hi> who encountred no other Ideas but thoſe of Love and Extaſie; he was tranſported with the many Charms he found in the beautiful <hi>Aſpatia.</hi> He fancy'd her his own, not dreaming of any Obſtacle that could oppoſe it; he conſider'd the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality of their Birth and Fortune, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency of the Match; and indulged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with all the tranſporting and delightful Raptures that proceed from thought.</p>
            <p>The next day was that great Solemnity, wherewith <hi>Alphonſo Henery</hi> entertain'd his new Queen <hi>Beatrice,</hi> Daughter to <hi>Alphonſo the Tenth,</hi> King of <hi>Caſtile;</hi> by whom that Noble Dowry, the Kingdom of <hi>Algaroes,</hi> was added to the Crown of <hi>Portugal.</hi> All the Nobility was there preſent to pay their Devoirs to the Queen. In particular, the illuſtrious Families of <hi>Almeyda,</hi> and that of the Marqueſs <hi>de Leganes,</hi> who was Father to our Cavalier <hi>Melantius.</hi> The Celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe Nuptials, would be too tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to recite; let it ſuffice, never was any thing more glorious, where <hi>Melantius</hi> made the moſt conſiderable Figure of the <hi>Beaux Eſprits,</hi> and <hi>Aſpatia</hi> of the <hi>Belles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The general approbation they receiv'd, did not a little contribute to augment the favourable Sentiments they had entertained for one another. And at the <hi>Tournament,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:151240:14"/>when <hi>Aſpatia</hi> beheld her young Heroe enter the Lift, (with an Aſpect that foretold the Miracles he perform'd) it was eaſie to read her Wiſhes in her Eyes, which were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly fixed upon him, and ſeem'd to move in the ſame Sphere with the Viciſſitudes of his Fortune. But oh! how her Heart danc'd when he came of Conquerour; the Air re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded with 10 Poeans to the Victor, and ecchoing Triumphs filled the breath of Fame; but his proudeſt Trophy was the Congra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulation he receiv'd from the fair <hi>Aſpatia;</hi> and without doubt, he was Gallant enough to attribute his good Fortune to the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of her Eyes.</p>
            <p>After ſome ſhort Preliminaries, theſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions broke up, to entertain the Ladies with a ſplendid Ball; and it was there <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantius</hi> determin'd to make an Offering of his panting Heart to the Deity he Worſhip'd: His kind Stars ſoon bleſs'd him with a lucky Opportunity; for <hi>Aſpatia</hi> being ſomewhat overheated with Dancing, was in motion with her Fan, which by chance ſhe let fall. <hi>Melantius</hi> was the fortunate Perſon that took it up, and delivering it with a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Bow, in a ſoft dying Tone; he ſaid, <hi>Ah! Madam, could you as eaſily reſtore my Heart, which I just now reſign'd an Offering at your Feet.</hi> She ſmil'd at the pretty Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry, and reply'd, <hi>I never retain any thing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151240:14"/>I cannot pretend a Property in;</hi> and would have declin'd a farther Diſcourſe: But he continu'd, <hi>That is as your Cruelty or Juſtice will determine: This I can affirm, it is no longer mine; and if your Severity will not think it worth your Charitable Protection, you ſhall behold it the most wretched Victim in the World.</hi> He waited for no anſwer, but taking hold of one corner of her Handkerchief, which he dexterouſly convey'd into his own Hands: <hi>'Tis but reaſonable, Madam,</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>to afford me ſome ſmall Relick, to guard that Breach, which otherwiſe you expoſe to the greatest danger imaginable.</hi> Altho' this did ſomething diſpleaſe her, it was impoſſible to retrieve it, without a publick view; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not offering at a recovery, ſhe ſuffered him to carry it off, tho' not without a great Reſentment, which appear'd in her angry Brow. <hi>Melantius,</hi> who was ſenſible of his fault, engaged with the reſt of the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and appeared no more that Night be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Aſpatia,</hi> but as a Criminal; only ſhe had the ſecret ſatisfaction of often ſeeing the Handkerchief diſplay'd to his Lips, and there moſt religiouſly ſaluted. The Depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the King and Queen, put a period to that Days Entertainment; and all the Company retired well diſpoſed to ſleep; nor did a thought moleſt <hi>Aſpatia,</hi> who enjoyed
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151240:15"/>a ſweet Recruit for the laſt Night's Tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Phoebus</hi> had already mounted the Olym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pick Palace, and made a conſiderable Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs in his Day's Circuit, when our love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Fair awaked, and called <hi>Laura</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire how the Day had paſt: After ſhe receiv'd ſatisfaction to ſome ſuch frivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Queſtions, <hi>Laura</hi> preſents her with a <hi>Billet-doux,</hi> which ſhe had juſt receiv'd from a Page of <hi>Melantius,</hi> who ſtill wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for an Anſwer: She took it with a panick fear, in hope and doubt, to find what it contain'd; but who can tell her pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Tranſport, when ſhe read what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>MELANTIUS <hi>to</hi> ASPATIA.</head>
                  <p>IF an Offender may have leave to plead for Mercy, have pity on a true Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. My Crime may be too Enormous to expect a Pardon; but I am ſure my Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is of as large a ſize. You have already ſufficiently puniſhed me, and that cruel Frown at parting ſtab'd deep into my Heart; nor could Poyſon, Daggers, or a thouſand Deaths
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:151240:15"/>be half ſo terrible. Let it ſuffice, I only live to receive my Sentence from thoſe dear Lips that can give Life even in the pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of my Death. My Life and Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs are abſolutely in your power; and if to Love with the most ſenſible Tenderneſs ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable, can offend; to Die, would be but the least part of my Duty: But if a Reſtora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my petty Theft can any way contribute to a Pardon, permit me this Afternoon to lay at your Feet both That and your Adoring Slave,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Melantius.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This paſſionate Declaration was ſo far from diſpleaſing, that it filled her with a Torrent of Joy, to find a Man ſo entirely at her Diſpoſe, whom Fate had already de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin'd her to Love; to deny his Viſit, was to rack her own Inclination, and to permit it too eaſily, would make the Conqueſt too cheap; however, this Conteſt did not long laſt, the irreſiſtable God bore ſway, and ſhe returned this Anſwer.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:151240:16"/>
                  <head>ASPATIA <hi>to</hi> ME<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LANTIUS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Am Confirmed, that in all points <hi>Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> is the most Gallant of Men; and where he offends, he makes but too ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Reparation: I can forgive without theſe Inſinuations you uſe to bribe a Pardon; but ſhall expect with the Return of my Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerchief, you deſist a Suit too inglorious for a Heroe.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Aſpatia.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Having diſpatched the Page, ſhe began to reflect how barbarouſly ſhe uſed <hi>Octavio</hi> in the mean time; but who can reſiſt the powerful influence of that little Tyrant, who models us after his own Chimera's? well may he be repreſented blind, not only for the inequality of Perſons that he wounds, but whoever is poſſeſſed of the ſame Malady, runs violently on, purſues the Object of their Affections, adheres to nothing but Almighty Love, and cannot ſee an Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour.</p>
            <p>Well, ſhe is reſolv'd to let <hi>Octavio</hi> ſtay a little for an Anſwer, being in ſome perplexity
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151240:16"/>what to write to him; ſhe baniſhed all trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome Thoughts, and wholly dedicated that Day to <hi>Melantius,</hi> who came dreſs'd with all the Gaiety of a young Bridegroom; enter'd the Room, with ten thouſand Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and paſſionately flings himſelf at her Feet; and having ſtole her Hand, he gently raiſed it to his trembling Lips, and ſtampt the Image of his Soul upon it. <hi>Aſpatia,</hi> who ſimpathized too feelingly with this Extaſie, was the firſt that by good fortune recovered her ſelf; and being oblig'd to take ſome notice, <hi>My Lord,</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>this is far from concurring with the Capitulations I propos'd. Oh! name them not;</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>forbid the Sun to ſhine, ſtop the bright Charioteer of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in his full Career, root up the Ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th from its Center, but never, never bid me ceaſe to Love; all theſe are more poſſible to be done, then not to Love the Adorable</hi> Aſpatia.</p>
            <p>She already felt a Commiſeration too ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to withſtand, but her unlucky Sex obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges her to act that hard Part, to appeaſe the deareſt of her Wiſhes: ſhe wore the Mask, and moſt ſeverely reprimanded him, conjur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him not to perſue ſo extravagant a Ral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery; or if it were ſincere, to avoid ſo fruitleſs an Amour: In ſhort, ſhe played the Tyrant, and inſulted over a Heart, whoſe ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Faculty was to ſerve her; but <hi>Melanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> could not yield to Deſpair, at every little
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151240:17"/>repulſe, and reſolved not to quit the Siege: He left her not that Evening, till he had brought her to a more gentle Humour; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that, not a Day paſſed wherein he failed to ſigh and plead. This tender Application engaged her to ſhew him indifferent Favours, till at laſt Time and Aſſiduity prevailed, and ſighing, dying, ſhe confeſſed ſhe Loved. It was then his Joy was without bounds, exalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed above a common Tranſport, he was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient for a Conſummation, and every Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute of delay was inſupportable; he inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Marqueſs <hi>de Leganes,</hi> that now he was ready to make a Reſignation of himſelf to the fair <hi>Aſpatia,</hi> and only waited his Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals to the Duke her Father. The Marqueſs was extreamly well pleaſed at his Son's reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to Marry, commended his Choice, applauded his Prudence, and without far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther demurs, he orders his Coach to be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and away to the Duke <hi>de Almydas,</hi> whom he had the fortune to find at home: Before they parted, occaſion preſented to promote the Unity of their Families: The Duke returned the Marqueſs all the Civility in the World; and tho' he did not abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly determine, he deſired time to conſider, which was more out of Ceremony, than any doubt or ſcruple; he knew the conveniency of the Alliance, and after pretenſions of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Conſideration, two or three Viſits brought it to a concluſion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:151240:17"/>Next there was a moſt glorious Preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for their Nuptials; in the mean time <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantius</hi> had free egreſs and regreſs to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of his Bliſs, where the bleſſed Hours were ſpent in gazing, wiſhing, and a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Toys that Lovers affect to pleaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, till the happier Minutes may be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved.</p>
            <p>Who would not conclude him now the happieſt of all Men, juſt ready to launch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Sea of Pleaſure, within reach of the wiſh'd for Haven, and not able to touch the Shore. Fate ſo order'd it that the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs <hi>de Leganes</hi> was taken violently ill, and in three or four days died: This put a ſtop to a farther proceeding, in the Hyme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nean Ceremonies, till a long Obſequies was celebrated to the Dead.</p>
            <p>'Tis impoſſible to tell how much <hi>Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> ſuffered at this time, not only for the loſs of ſo dear a Parent, but at the delay of ſo many Joys; which without doubt would have been a kind Ingredient, and have helpt down the bitter Pill of Affliction, with leſs regret; there's no Life, no ſupport for him, whilſt abſent from <hi>Aſpatia:</hi> But the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of his Affairs forbidding his ſtay, the better to bear this parting, he begs her Picture, which ſhe grants, but at the ſame time intreats for his: This was his conſtant Companion in all Adventures, never from his
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151240:18"/>Boſom, ſlept and converſed with him, miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated his Misfortunes and increaſed his Joys; and ſo ſtrong was his Imagination, that he fancied it bore part in all his Change of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune.</p>
            <p>The time was now come, that the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs was convey'd to <hi>Porto,</hi> there to be Inter'd, in a Tomb belonging to their Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors. Whilſt theſe Rites were performing, <hi>Melantius,</hi> to give vent to the exceſs of Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row that oppreſſed him, walkt out one E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening on the Banks of <hi>Duero,</hi> whoſe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Streams runs by the Walls of <hi>Porto;</hi> and moving on with a ſoft eaſie pace, ſilent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entertaining himſelf with Contemplation of his future Fate, was rous'd from the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byſs of Thought he was loſt in, by a Sigh that ſeem'd to pierce the Air; this made him curious to diſcover what Perſon it was that gave ſuch evident tokens of Diſtreſs: He had not gone far before he diſcovered a Cavalier, who lay upon the Graſs, with his Face towards the River; he appeared to be very tall, and his Hair black; he had a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in his Hand, which having read, he flung his Arm down with a little force, and cryed, <hi>Where must we ſeek for Vertue? Is there ſuch a thing in being? Or, is it but a Notion? 'Tis evident it's not to be found within this Globe of Earth, if it can fail in Cruel Fair</hi> Aſpatia. Theſe words were very much ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:151240:18"/>to <hi>Melantius,</hi> who heard one ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and as he hoped for another <hi>Aſpatia,</hi> he was a true Lover, and did not want for a thouſand perplexing Fears and Doubts, at the Name of his Miſtreſs, yet were they not ſo violent as to diſturb his attention to the Cavalier who thus went on: <hi>All things in Nature look ſo huſh and calm, and not a breath of wind diſturbs the gentle Air, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Horizon is all ſerene, nor do theſe dewy Sheets one wrinkle wear; and yet the Pertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bations of my Breast, are able to affect the World around me: Have I not ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, implored, and wiſht in vain? And am I now grown ſo Contemptible not to deſerve an Anſwer? Oh! Where are all thoſe pitying Looks and Glances, that uſed to wound <hi>Octavio</hi> with delight? Was my Hopes exalted to that height, to make my Fall mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e deſperate, and upbraid me with too great Preſumption? Theſe Characters! Theſe dear Characters! can Witneſs I was not once indifferent to her. Support me, feeble Limbs, once more to</hi> Lisbon, <hi>and I'll diſcharge you e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver from a future Service.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The naming of <hi>Lisbon,</hi> gave a freſh Alarm to <hi>Melantius,</hi> and had like to have deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him up to as much Deſparation as the other: He was fixing direful Thoughts, when he perceived the Cavalier to riſe and come forward, which obliged him to retire ſome diſtance, till he ſaw the way he would
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:151240:19"/>take, being reſolved to track him, and if poſſible, to find out the Myſtery of his Trouble; with that deſign he ſuffered him to advance to the utmoſt limit of his ſight; who returned the ſame way that <hi>Melantius</hi> came, with his Arms folded, and his Eyes fixed upon the Earth. In this poſture he had not gone far, before he diſcerned ſomething on the ground which caſt a reſplendant light, that ſhow'd it to be of conſiderable value; and having taken it up, it appeared an Eb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bony-Caſe inlayed with Gold, and ſet round with Diamonds; the outſide Glories were inferiour to what he found within, and it requires a more Polite Pen to diſplay the Wonder, Extaſie and Jealouſie, that poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his mind, to find the lively Protraicture of <hi>Aſpatia</hi> painted there. <hi>Great Gods!</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>Where will my various Fortune end? Am I beholden to ye for this Preſent, or is it lost by my more happy Rival? Perhaps</hi> Aſpatia <hi>may be near this place, and by ſome lucky Accident have dropt it: But Oh! that hope is vaniſh'd 're it is conceiv'd;</hi> Octavio <hi>dare not think ſhe who could ſuffer him to Languiſh theſe two Months, without the least of a relenting Pity, could be induced to ſet a foot near</hi> Porto, <hi>whilst it contained her much contemned Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirer: Yet, whatever Chance has ſent thee, thou art welcome.</hi> Aſpatia <hi>may be Cruel to the highest degree, but you are innocent, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:151240:19"/>no Ingrate; you ſmile, and pleaſe me with a thouſand Graces; and ſhould I lay you near my panting Heart, you would no way reſist, but yield, and there receive warmth from my raging fire: Nay, ſhould I raviſh here ten thouſand Kiſſes, they were all my own, without the least repulſe: Why then, dear Flatterer, we will never part, but cheat my childiſh Hope with theſe Deluſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He was ſeated under a Tree, pleaſing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with abundance of ſuch wild Diſcourſes. When <hi>Melantius</hi> miſſed his Picture, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned with all the Concern in the World, to the place where he diſcovered the Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier; and having ſearch'd diligently, and not finding it, his fears ſuggeſts to him a thouſand Doubts: Sometimes he fancies that he had dropt it as he came, and probably 'tis found by ſome poor Peaſant; who, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted with the Treaſure, would conceal it, from all poſſible means of regaining: Then he imagines it in the hands of the Cavalier, whom by this time he had loſt ſight of, and knows not where to find: This made him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>double his Pace, and with all the ſpeed he could, endeavour to recover the Town be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was Hous'd; yet not ſo expeditiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as to hinder him from a ſlight ſearch as he paſſed. Being thus imploy'd, and his thoughts wholly fixed on his Loſs, he was ſtartled at the unexpected ſight of the Cavalier, who ſtill lay under the Tree, adoring the lovely
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:151240:20"/>Picture of <hi>Aſpatia. Melantius</hi> filled with Joy to have found it, yet Jealouſie and Spleen to ſee it there, went up to him; and with a haſty Voice demanded the Piece. But the Cavalier drown'd in his thoughts, anſwers to ſome former Ejaculations of his own; <hi>The Gods ſhall never retrieve thee.</hi> This rude reply, (as <hi>Melantius</hi> apprehended it to be) ſo inraged him, that without any more words he had recourſe to his Sword; bidding the Cavalier (if he dar'd) riſe, and defend it; who being recovered from his waking Dream by this fierce Attack, tho' not knowing the reaſon, yet ſeeing there was no time for Parley, he Drew in his own Defence; at firſt only parrying to avoid the Paſſes that were made at him, but finding his Enemy too reſolute to be play'd with, he was forc'd to endeavour his Diſpatch, to ſecure his own Life.</p>
            <p>This rencounter was maintained with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual Fortune for ſome time, by theſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, till <hi>Melantius</hi> feeling himſelf bleed in the right Arm, renew'd his force; Shame and Anger made him deſperate; ſo that by a thruſt under the left Pap, he had the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to ſee the Cavalier fall; but <hi>Melantius</hi> (who was in all points truly Noble and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous, ran to his Aſſiſtance, deplor'd his Fate, begg'd his Pardon, and blam'd him for being ſo refractory. The Cavalier had
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151240:20"/>neither Sence, nor Strength to liſten to his many relenting, tho' ineffectual Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, yet perceiving him willing to ſerve him, with broken Sentences and Signs, he deſired to be carry'd to a little Cott within a ſtones throw, which ſtood alone and obſcure at the foot of a Hill. <hi>Melantius</hi> having diſcry'd the place, was in diſtreſs how to convey him thither; when he beheld an old Man driv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the Hill a few poor Goats; he called to him, and deſired his help, he was very ready to aſſiſt, and withal told him, what his humble Roof could afford, was at their Command; but he feared it had nothing to recommend it but Retirement, being three Miles off the City, poorly furniſh'd, and ill provided. <hi>Melantius</hi> thankt him for his fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Relief, and return'd to the place where he had left the Cavalier juſt expiring. When the old Man drew near to diſcern the Face of this Unfortunate, he burſt into a ſhower of Tears; and cryed, <hi>Ah! poor</hi> Don Pedro; <hi>What Cruel Hand has deſtroyed the best of Men? Now may theſe Shades be curſed, whoſe dear delightful Retreat has be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed thee, like a Syren, to thy utter ruine: Did I this Morning leave thee freſh and well, to bring thee home a dead and helpleſs Corpſe? Oh! had I never known thy Vertues, I had never miſſed thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:151240:21"/>His grief ſpoke a ſenſible ſorrow, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering a ſpeedy help was required, <hi>Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> interrupted him to bear the Cavalier to the Houſe, where they layed him on a Bed, and covered up his Wound cloſe from the Air; <hi>Melantius</hi> likewiſe bound up his own Arm, and the old Man called a Lad, whom they ſent to the Town to bring a Chirurgeon with all ſpeed and privacy; in the mean time careful not to diſturb the wounded Cavalier, who had little other ſign of Life than a trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled breathing; they retire to the Door of the Hutt, where <hi>Melantius</hi> enquired of the old Man what he knew concerning him, he was nothing ſcrupulous to declare his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance of him, and thus began.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>I have lived upon this ſpot theſe fourſcore years, never in plenty, nor ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did I want; by Trade a Fiſherman, my Family once large, which I maintained by my daily Labour, till the Supream Powers were pleaſed to reduce it to the poor Lad you have ſeen, who is my Grand-child; he is now about fifteen years of Age, him have I brought up to the ſame Slavery, being in no Capacity to do better for him; we live alone, and eat what we earn with ſweet content. One-Evening, as we were fiſhing, two Leagues from this place, was the first time we ſaw this</hi> Don Pedro, <hi>ſitting at the foot of a Rock melancholy, and ſighing to the Winds; but he took no notice of us that time,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:151240:21"/>nor ſeveral times after, when we have found him in the ſame place, ſometimes reading, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times complaining at his hard Fate; one Day he ſeemed diverted with our Sport, and deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>red to Board us; we put to Shore and took him in, and he continued with us till towards Night, enquiring of my Life, my Family, my Abode, in all which he was particularly pleaſed at my unambitious Mind, and free Content; he told me I was Rich and Happy becauſe I coveted no more. For that Night we parted, and having liberally rewarded us, he returned from whence he came, but bid us not fail to meet him the next Day, having promiſed to viſit our homely Habitation: We fetched him punctually at the appointed place, and brought him to this Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Shore, where he was ſo taken with the Retirement, and innocent Life, being a Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery to his Grief, that he could not part from us; but this mean Room (he now lies in) was his Lodging, being the best we have. Six Weeks has he been here, in which time his Diverſion was to Walk alone, early and late, ſometimes he would Fiſh with us, he far'd as we did; all I could learn relating to himſelf, or Country, is, that his Name is</hi> Pedro, <hi>a Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard Born; he was very inquiſitive after Letters, and ſent the Boy every Night to</hi> Porto <hi>to enquire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this time the Chyrurgeon was come, whom <hi>Melantius</hi> brib'd to Secrecy; having
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:151240:22"/>prob'd the Wound of the Cavalier, they were greatly incouraged to find it not mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal; but his exceſſive bleeding had already reduced him ſo low, he could not ſpeak, but fainted ſeveral times in their Arms. <hi>Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> (tho' he did not want for Jealouſie that this was his Rival) yet conſidered his Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune with much trouble, he ſtayed till he was Dreſſed, and after applying ſomething to his own Arm, and leaving a Charge to the old Man to be careful of him, he returned with the Chyrurgeon to <hi>Porto,</hi> promiſing to be with them early the next Morning. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſhort Devoir pay'd to the Marqueſs <hi>de Leganez,</hi> he retired to his Bed, to Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate on the Days Adventure, and altho' his Malady requir'd reſt, his diſtracted thoughts could not permit of any reſpite, but flew more ſwift than the fleeting Minutes; he was impatient for the Day, that he might a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain viſit the wounded Cavalier, who (he hoped) would be in a Condition to relate ſome part of his Life, at leaſt tell him, why he would not part with the Picture but by Compulſion.</p>
            <p>Scarce had the pale-fac'd Empreſs of the Night, drawn her Sable Curtains, but <hi>Melantius</hi> was up, and arrived at the poor Manſion; juſt as bright <hi>Sol</hi> had tip'd the top of <hi>Olympius</hi> with his golden Beams, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving before taken care all Neceſſaries ſhould
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:151240:22"/>be brought; the Cavalier, whom he found ſomething revived by a little Sleep he had gotten, and both able to look up and ſpeak. <hi>Melantius</hi> enquired of his Health, withal ſignifying ſome Joy for this ſmall Amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but an undiſſembled Concern for his Misfortune. The Cavalier was amazed at this great Civility, from a Perſon he imagin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed had uſed him the moſt unreaſonable of all Men. <hi>Sir,</hi> (ſaid he, in a weak faint voice) <hi>how much I receive from you now, can only be repayed by a bare acknowledgment, and I must attribute this Favour altogether to your Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity, being as much at a loſs for any Merit of mine to deſerve it, as I am at our late Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel. Melantius</hi> as much puzzel'd at theſe Expreſſions, was apt to believe a Fevor had ſeized his Head, but conſidering 'em ſpoke with an Air that ſhewed a great Moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and peculiar Grace, he was obliged to anſwer in this manner. <hi>Nothing could have provoked my Sword against a Perſon of your Worth, but the refuſing to reſtore this Picture, which is my only preſent Felicity.</hi> The Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier aſſured him he did not hear it demanded. <hi>But, Sir,</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>dare you ſo far trust my Fidelity, to inform me whoſe it is, and how it became yours? Melantius</hi> very willingly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd; <hi>It is a Lady's, whoſe Fame is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined to the ſcanty limits of one Kingdom, but univerſally admired: She is the Daughter to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151240:23"/>the Duke</hi> de Almeyda; <hi>and were it not for the Jilting Tricks of Fortune, I ſhould now ſtile her my Wife; her own Hand recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it to me, when the Death of the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> de Leganes <hi>(from whom I received my being) put a ſtop to our Marriage, which ſhould have been Conſummated within a Week.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Cavalier, whoſe Attention was inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted with a Torrent of Sighs, at this laſt Accent of <hi>Melantius,</hi> reſigned his Life, or at leaſt it appeared ſo, when all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> induſtry that was uſed could not recal his Spirits; but juſt when they diſcovered ſome glimer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Hopes, his Soul ſhrank back as in the Abhorrance of the World; but the aſſiſtance of the Chirurgion, who was now come, was ſo effectual, that no longer could the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe of his anxious Trouble repel his Art, but in ſpite of himſelf, was his Life thruſt back, to die ten thouſand Deaths: With the firſt breath he recover'd, he exclaim'd againſt the Cruel Fair, and blames Heaven for making her the brighteſt of her Sex, without diſperſing their Divineſt Attributes upon her. <hi>Oh! Why!</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>Why was ſhe created ſo Divinely Glorious? (That Gods themſelves would have been proud to have layn at her Feet, adoring Captives) and not be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with unblemiſh'd and unſhaken Virtue? Is the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e no Bolt of Hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en that ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>kes with Fate, but must it light on miſerable</hi> Octavio? <hi>Ah!
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:151240:23"/>falſe Ingrate, now triumph in thy Injures, and with thy inſulting ſcorn cruſh thy loathed Victim lower than the Grave.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Every word he ſpoke, was like Darts to <hi>Melantius,</hi> and almoſt pierced him through; nor was his ſtaggering Thoughts longer in diſpute, if this was his Rival: Alas! he was too terribly convinc'd; yet being nearly concern'd to have a more ample ſatisfaction, which he could not learn from this confuſed Diſcourſe; he had ſo much command of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as to endeavour to moderate the exceſs of his Paſſion, and recal his Peace: But few things are of ſufficient power to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade a deſpairing Man into Reaſon; he looks upon himſelf as the loweſt and vileſt Inſect; miſerable, deſpis'd, and ruin'd; nay, loſt in a Miſt of wild Horrours. In this rage he continues to curſe the malice of his Stars, ſometimes pouring out Execrations on himſelf, for being too unworthy to poſſeſs ſo Divine Treaſures. Then again charging her with being Falſe, Cruel, Inhumane and Unjuſt. <hi>Now</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>if this Soul dare re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in this deſolate Body, who can be more wretched? But I will never fall ſo low, and abject: Nor can I bear, (even tho' her Charms are by her falſhood almost lost;) that another ſhould raviſh them from me. But will the Gods permit ſuch things to proſper? On whom we Mortals do rely for Juſtice.</hi> No endeavour
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:151240:24"/>they could uſe, could bring him into a cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Humour, or engage him to ſuffer his Wound to be dreſs'd; he ſtill oppos'd it, and tore the Plaiſters off as they were apply'd. <hi>Melantius</hi> alledg'd, That probably there might be a miſtake. <hi>Are you ſure</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>this is the ſame</hi> Aſpatia? <hi>If you knew this Hand,</hi> (he reply'd) <hi>which I believe you are no Stranger to, your Doubts are evidently reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</hi> With that he deliver'd him a Letter, in which there was ſuch tender Expreſſions, that could proceed from nothing but Love: As he read, every Letter grated his Soul, to find ſuch conſiderable Favours laviſh'd on another. <hi>Oh! Poor</hi> Melantius; (ſaid he, fighing to himſelf) <hi>thou hast but blown up the Embers, in the abſence of this Cavalier; for 'tis impoſſible ſuch ſubſtantial Love, could va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh with a flaſh; even when he was within reach of enjoying all that his Soul could wiſh for. But why ſhould I complain? Is it not for me, ſhe forgoes all theſe Engagements? If it is a Frailty, 'tis to make me happy? But how am I ſure ſhe doth not yet retain ſome Inclination, for the once lov'd</hi> Octavio? <hi>Who by one melt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing glance, may perhaps kindle afreſh her expiring Flame. How may I believe that a Heart which could once play falſe, ſhould conſtant prove to me? What Charms has poor</hi> Melantius <hi>to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure it? Only Exceſs of Love.</hi> Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding theſe uneaſie Thoughts, he reſolves
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:151240:24"/>to ſee her ſuddenly; and if her Plea con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd him of her Innocence, ſhe ſhould from him receive an everlaſting faithful Love. Yet this ungenerous Proceeding with <hi>Octavio,</hi> ſhock'd his tendereſt Sentiments; and were he not already the moſt amorous of Men, he had declined a Beauty that could be guilty of ſuch pitiful Conduct: He was throughly convinc'd how much the Cavalier might have hoped for; yet conſidering himſelf the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Man, he reflects on it with Partiality. After much intreaty they prevailed with him to be dreſſed, and finding him inclinable to repoſe, (which was but a feigned ſhow, that he might have the melancholy liberty of his own Thoughts) they left him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Melantius</hi> returning to <hi>Porto,</hi> in his way met the Boy with a Letter directed to <hi>Don Pedro,</hi> and knowing the Hand to be <hi>Aſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi>'s, who could blame his Curioſity, in this juncture of Affairs for opening it? She had been in a Sea of Troubles and Fears in his Abſence, conſidering what would be the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent of <hi>Octavio</hi>'s Paſſion, ſhould ſhe not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer his Letter: She knew he could not long be a Stranger to her Amours with <hi>Melantius,</hi> and therefore ſhe thought cunningly to pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liate the Story to him her ſelf; with this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign ſhe had framed, (with all the Subtilty and Craft that could be invented) a way to break to him the dreadful Secret; and in order to that, had thus writ.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:151240:25"/>
                  <head>ASPATIA <hi>to</hi> OCTAVIO.</head>
                  <p>THink me not <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngrateful, when I ſend the Generous <hi>Octavio,</hi> the best of Wiſhes. Oh! how unaccountable are the Circumſtances of our Lives and Paſſions? Let it ſuffice, 'tis you, and only you, can make my future Days happy, or miſerable: I have Wonders to tell you, and beg that ſpeedily you come to <hi>Lisbon. Laura</hi> ſhall meet you, at the uſual Rendezvous, and conduct you to the loſt and confuſed</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Aſpatia.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This indeed new model'd his Reſolutions; and inſtead of ſeeing her, his deſign is now wholly to abandon her, having diſcovered (as he thinks) a ſufficient Demonſtration of her Falſeneſs; Rage and Reſentment, fill'd his Soul: <hi>Am I at last</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>abuſed and forlorn? No, falſe One, you may triumph, but never ſhall inſult over the wronged</hi> Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius; <hi>for from this Minute, I will ſhun thy falſe deluding Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus fully determined, he goes home; no reſt could he take, various were his thoughts, and as various his Reſolutions; yet all deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined in that point, of never ſeeing more the Fair Deceiver. How to diſpoſe of himſelf he was not long at a ſtand, when he reflected that all <hi>Italy</hi> was in Arms, and that the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:151240:25"/>betwixt the <hi>Pittis,</hi> and that Compleat Heroe and Champion for his Country, <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renzo de Medici,</hi> the <hi>Tuſcan</hi>-War that was then afoot, the Republick of <hi>Venice</hi> that was likewiſe engaged, would give him a glorious Diverſion, from his perplexing Croſſes, eſpecially too ſince the <hi>Turks</hi> gave them new Fears, by menacing the remainder of thoſe Iſlands, which they held in the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chipelago.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus poſitively reſolv'd, he writes a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the <hi>Marquis de Leganes;</hi> in which he deſired him not to be concern'd, at his ſudden Departure; ſince he had made a Vow to perform ſome Religious Duties, not only relating to himſelf, but for the good of his dead Mother's Soul; withal telling him the reaſon why he did not take his leave, as his Duty requir'd, was fear of being op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in that which nothing ought to avert; and in his abſence, which he hoped would not be long, his Prayers ſhould conſtantly be offered up for his Proſperity: Likewiſe, that he ſhould go nigh to ſteer his firſt Courſe to our Lady of <hi>Loretto.</hi> This being prepared, he call'd a Servant whom he could truſt, and having related to him his deſign, ordered him with ſpeed and privacy to hire a Feleuqua at the nigheſt Port. Whilſt his Man (whoſe Name was <hi>Montal</hi>) was thus employ'd: <hi>Melantius</hi> writes to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:151240:26"/>
               <hi>Aſpatia</hi> this Letter, and in it incloſes hers, which he had intercepted going to <hi>Octavio.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>MELANTIUS <hi>to</hi> ASPATIA.</head>
                  <p>YOU must pardon me (Madam) if I dare not encounter thoſe dangerous Eyes once more to take my last Farewel; believe me, 'tis with great Regret I quit this Kingdom, and had <hi>Aſpatia</hi> been true, not Empires heaped on Empires, could have tempted me to leave her. At the ſame time I must applaud your Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity to the unhappy happy <hi>Octavio,</hi> who by a dire Miſtake of Fortune, has ſuffered under my Hand, yet not ſo cruelly as by your Eyes: 'Tis time to abate the Tyranny you have uſed, and reſtore a Heart he once has been poſſeſs'd of. If I have wrong'd him in intercepting this Billet, y ur Mercy which I am ſure will not be wanting, can calm the raging Feavor in his Blood. Yet to make a Reparation for my Fault, but more to gratifie your dearest Wiſh, by my Abſence you ſhall fear no Obſtacle to moleſt your Tranquility; and where-ever I am, ſpight of myſelf, I am the lost confuſed <hi>Aſpatia</hi>'s</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Melantius.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Soon after <hi>Montal</hi> returned with the News of a Merchant-Veſſel that only waited the next fair Wind to hoiſt Sail for the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:151240:26"/>
               <hi>Streights,</hi> which they hourly expected. <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantius</hi> got all things in readineſs, having con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived juſt as he Embark'd, to ſend his two Letters forward. About the hour of Twelve, a Mariner came to give <hi>Montal</hi> warning, that the more ſpeed they made the better. The Night ſhrouded with her gloomy Vall, and a freſh Breeze of Wind repreſented to <hi>Melantius</hi> (as he made to the Port) not the calmeſt Reflections; yet with a Noble Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very that always attended him, he Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bark'd; where we will leave him on his Voyage, and relate what was done in the mean time at Home.</p>
            <p>Early the next Morning the Marqueſs <hi>de Leganes</hi> had his Letter, which extreamly ſtartled him, but being a Pious Man, and conſidering the conſequence of the Buſineſs, he the eaſier diſpenc'd with his Abſence; and what made him the more credulous, was his Engagement with <hi>Aſpatia,</hi> which he judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be too dear a Tye, to quit upon a Whimſy: Thus with moderation did the Marqueſs bear the Abſence of his Son, but for what poor unfortunate <hi>Aſpatia</hi> ſuffered, (who knew too well the cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> cauſe) I dare not undertake here to diſplay. Only the weight of her Misfortunes was of power to ſink a World. A Death-like Cold ſeiz'd her Heart, her every Faculty loſt their uſe at the News of his Flight. In this manner
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:151240:27"/>ſhe continued for a long time, till her ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Paſſion forc'd a vent; then how often did ſhe blame her unhappy Conduct, raging and almoſt frantick, ſhe deliver'd herſelf up to the extremity of an immoderate Sorrow: No Name was too hideous for ſuch black In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude, as ſhe term'd it, nor no Wiſh too hard or ſevere; at the ſame time forgetting her unkind uſage to <hi>Octavio.</hi> There was not one Argument <hi>Laura</hi> omitted to reſtore her Peace, but to no purpoſe, her Reaſon was loſt; ſhe beheld her ſelf fallen from the height of Bliſs to the moſt abject Misfortune, and in her wild thoughts ſhe ſaw the Man ſhe loved, and hourly languiſhed for, in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Country, pleaſant, and diverting himſelf in Company with all the Ladies of Beauty, Wit, and Fortune, whilſt ſhe was flighted and abandoned by him, deſerted, and foraken: How this rack'd the utmoſt faculty of her Soul? <hi>Oh!</hi> Melantius; <hi>Oh! Cruel</hi> Melantius, did ſhe cry, <hi>How miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? How wretched miſerable have you made me? If I have been unjust, Heaven knows it is not to thee; then blame thy ſelf, thy dear engaging Self, that has betray'd</hi> Aſpatia <hi>to thoſe baſe Characters of Falſe, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njust, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngenerous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Paſſion continued ſo violent, that ſhe found it impoſſible to appear before the Duke that Day, without expoſing her Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:151240:27"/>having loſt her Maſter-piece of Diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation and Cunning, which by ſome is attributed as incident to the Sex, too ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble was her Affliction to bear diſguiſe, and therefore to conceal it from the Duke, whom ſhe knew would ſearch too nicely into the dreadful Cauſe, ſhe ſent <hi>Laura</hi> to acquaint him ſhe was indiſpoſed, immediately retiring to her Bed, in expectation of a Viſit, knowing him to be the moſt indulgent of Fathers: Not long after he came reading of a Letter he had juſt receiv'd, and having enquired and adviſed about her Health, <hi>This Letter comes</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>from the Marqueſs</hi> de Leganes, <hi>wherein he acquaints me of a ſhort Voyage his Son has taken to the Chappel of</hi> Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retto; <hi>but, I believe</hi> (continued he with a Smile) <hi>your Intelligence has been more ſpeedy.</hi> At this ſecond Confirmation and killing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful News, ſhe could hardly ſupport her ſelf, and as he preſt on to know if ſhe had been before informed, ſhe felt the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt difficulty and pain to force but thoſe words, <hi>I was.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Duke having ſome gueſs at the nature of her Malady, left her to gain ſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, or rather to the freedom of her own Thoughts. No ſooner had he quitted the Room but ſhe called <hi>Laura</hi> to her, and with an eaſie Look, as if ſhe had maſter'd ſome difficulty, ſpoke to her in this manner:</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:151240:28"/>
               <hi>Since I have confided in thee as to all the Circumſtances of my Life, ſo must you now aſſist me in this last and most Deſperate: I Love, and you are no Stranger to the Extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of my Paſſion, my Life, my Honour, my Fame, are but falſe Idols to that Potent God: Tell me then, Can I live and not poſſeſs</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantius? <hi>That dear</hi> Melantius, <hi>whoſe Soul once mov'd with the ſame tender melting touch as mine. Oh! 'tis impoſſible; he thinks me Falſe, Perfidious, or he had never left me: Shall I then live with this black Infamy, and not right my ſelf? No, I will ſeek him to the utmost Verge of Earth, and there proclaim my Innocency; then if his Heart ſhould prove imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>netrable, and obdurate, my Death ſhall convince him of the direful Truth; and my wrong'd Ghost ſhall be ever before his Eyes, raving for Juſtice and Revenge, perplex his future Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laura</hi> gave her ſelf no trouble to diſwade her from this Exploit, believing it no other then a Chimera ſhe would never put in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution; But ſhe found her ſelf miſtaken, it was what had taken deep root and fixt in her Reſolution, ſhe perſiſted in it daily, and then ſhe failed not to lay before her the danger and hazard, but chiefly the falſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions would be made of ſuch an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant Action. <hi>Aſpatia</hi> was deaf to all Advice, and only made anſwer, She would
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:151240:28"/>not be diverted from her Deſign, tho' ſhe was forced to adventure alone. When <hi>Laura</hi> found her ſo fully determined, ſhe aſſured her, nothing could have that face of diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, or terrour, to make her decline her in the moſt deſperate Attempt; but hoping her care in reminding her of what might prove to her Diſadvantage, ſhould not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, ſhe poſitively conſents to obey her Commands.</p>
            <p>Thus ſatisfy'd with <hi>Laura</hi>'s Compliance, the next Conſultation was to get Mens Cloaths, the eaſier to diſguiſe their Flight, and moſt commodious for their adventurous Travels. This Task was left to <hi>Laura,</hi> as likewiſe to hire a Veſſel to Tranſport 'em to any Port in <hi>Italy,</hi> who performed very punctually all her Commands, and pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Viſit to ſome Relations for two or three Days, by <hi>Aſpatia</hi>'s Connivance, ſhe went directly to <hi>Setuval,</hi> a famous Haven about 20 Miles from <hi>Lisbon,</hi> where ſhe ſecured a ſmall Feleuqua for their purpoſe, and alſo placed Horſes in the Rode for their more ſpeedy conveyance thither. The Wind ſat fair every Hour ſhe was there, which obliged her to make a quick return to <hi>Lisbone,</hi> to inform <hi>Aſpatia,</hi> and aſſiſt her Flight.</p>
            <p>Night being the time for performing of ſuch Projects, they waited wiſh great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience and panick fears till it came, in the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:151240:29"/>mean time providing good ſtore of Gold and Jewels, the moſt portable and neceſſary Luggage, and being thus Knight-Errantly Equip'd, they ſally'd out, and at two Miles Stage took Horſe, and rid full ſpeed to <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuval;</hi> they arrived there about four a Clock, was Embark'd with the Courage of Heroins, and a fair way under Sail e're they were miſſed at home. But yet too ſoon was the fatal News ſpread throughout all <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal,</hi> for the Duke not ſeeing nor hearing from his Daughter the next Day, conclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her not well, went (as was his uſual Cuſtom) to her Apartment to viſit her, but not finding her there, he was much ſurprized, and ſeeing a Note lie on the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble he took it up, which to his greater Wonder, he found ſubſcribed to himſelf; wherein ſhe acquainted him ſhe had left the Kingdom, but had no way left to excuſe her Flight, but that Almighty Love was the powerful Cauſe, whoſe Paſſions and Effects were ever unaccountable, and begg'd him, if he could, retain a thought of his own former Joys, he would be ſo Charitable to recollect them in her defence, and believe ſhe left ſo good a Father, with the greateſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence imaginable; concluding with her Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition to indulge himſelf, and bear her Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence with moderation, and a charitable O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of her, giving him ſome hopes of a
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:151240:29"/>ſpeedy return, which ſhould compenſate for all her imprudence: But alas! This was of little force or efficacy; for the immoderate Grief, Anguiſh, and Shame which poſſeſs'd the Duke, (not only for the loſs of a Child he had built his chief felicity on, but at the Diſhonour of his Family, which could never be retriev'd) was not with eaſe to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay'd: He conſider'd her the Bloom of all <hi>Portugal,</hi> celebrated for her Beauty, and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſally admired; but when he came to reflect what a Blot ſhe had given all theſe Advantages, he could hardly ſupport the Trouble. There was no Port throughout the Kingdom he failed to ſend to, with Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to ſearch all Tranſport-Ships; all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence imaginable was uſed, but to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; our <hi>Amazons</hi> were fled beyond recal, their Habits taking off all Suſpition.</p>
            <p>Being thus deſtitute of Comfort, he found himſelf not Phyloſopher ſufficient, to bear with tranquility, ſo great a Misfortune, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in a place where he had all Eyes upon him, he therefore retired to a curious, tho' ſolitary Seat he had ſome twelve Miles from the Port of <hi>Ville-neue,</hi> where he paſs'd his Days recluſe from the World, with great Devotion and Acts of Charity, only now and then a ſelect Friend, in particular the Marqueſs <hi>de Leganes,</hi> who was herein greatly intereſted, a fit Companion to lament with
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:151240:30"/>him the unfortunate Conduct of both their Children: But what the more confounded the Marqueſs was, he lately had an account his Son was long ſince arrived at <hi>Leghorn,</hi> and after viſiting ſome of thoſe Holy Places he had promiſed, he had put himſelf in the <hi>Gens d'Arms</hi> of the <hi>Florentines,</hi> under <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renzo de Medici;</hi> where he did thoſe Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, I ſhall have no occaſion to ſpeak of here.</p>
            <p>But to return to <hi>Aſpatia,</hi> whoſe Voyage for the beſt part was pleaſant and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, they apprehended themſelves paſt all danger, being within ten Leagues or leſs of <hi>Leghorn,</hi> when a boiſterous Storm aroſe, and ſo violent a Tempeſt, that it terrify'd the moſt daring Mariner; the Seas ran Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains high, and the Heavens clattered out Peals of Thunder; and notwithſtanding they were ſo nigh the Shore, they were again drove out to Sea; and finding the Storm grow louder and more dreadful, they cut their Main-Maſt by the Board, and ſtrove to lay their Veſſel at Hull, whilſt all Hands were at work to furl their Sails, ſhe ſprang two Leaks, and it was with much ado, by the incredible labour and induſtry of the Seamen, who were continually plying the Pump, ſhe was kept above Water.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:151240:30"/>This was a ſad diſcouragement to our <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazones,</hi> (whom, tho' I cannot affirm, wiſh'd themſelves on their own Native Soil) yet none can blame them for being diſmay'd, when even the Tritons and Dolphins were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed. This Tempeſt laſted full ſix Hours, all which time it ſeemed to threaten them with immediate Deſtruction, at length it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to clear up to Windward, the Wind a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated, and in little time they made Land, tho' diſtant from the deſign'd Shore. They wrought luſtily for their Deliverance, and recover'd a rocky and dangerous Haven, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the State of <hi>Naples,</hi> call'd, <hi>Fuz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zuelo.</hi> The Feleuqua had done its laſt Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in bringing them ſafe to Land, her Rud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der being ſpent, and ſhe ſo much diſabled, ſhe was incapable of further Service, and lay a diſmal Memorandum of their paſt Danger with her Keel upward upon the Sands.</p>
            <p>With Joy they Landed, tho' feeble and faint, with little Nouriſhment, and hard Work, they in the Storm being forc'd to fling over Board moſt of their Proviſions to lighten the Veſſel. This was a place which obliged every one to ſhift for themſelves; being none acquainted with the Country. There were few other Paſſengers than <hi>Aſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> who now went by the Name of <hi>Don Lelio,</hi> and <hi>Laura</hi> by that of <hi>Carlo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:151240:31"/>Wildneſs, Wants, Barrenneſs, and innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable Calamities were ſeated here, which dreadful appearance encouraged the Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-beaten and diſtreſſed Saylors, with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to ſcale thoſe deſperate and ſtupen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Mountains, in purſuit of Food and Life; but this Atchievement had too many Difficulties and Terrors to be attempted by <hi>Don Lelio,</hi> who was driven to that extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to beg when they had allay'd their own Hunger, ſome one would be ſo Charitable to return with Relief, and aſſiſt them up that deſperate Precipice, yet before they depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to prevent any Outrage which might be offer'd, he diſtributed Gold largely amongſt them, and aſſured them he had but a ſmall parcel left for the ſupplying his own Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, the Quantity, and Freeneſs where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with it was given, eaſily confirm'd them in this belief, and there was not one but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed an Expeditious Return with the firſt Proviſions they found. Thus did this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant Paſſion reduce the Tender, Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful, and much to be pitty'd <hi>Don Lelio</hi> to all the Diſtreſs of Hunger and Cold; nay, expoſed to a Multitude of other Dangers; yet nothing made ſo cruel an Impreſſion as the Abſence of <hi>Melantius.</hi> Her Heart was not ſo obdurate, as to bear ſuch ſenſible af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions without Tears, which were ſhed in abundance by them both, to ſee themſelves
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:151240:31"/>left on a naked Rock, deſtitute of all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and likely to become a Prey to ſome furious wild Beaſt: Thus loaden with fears and grief, they imparted their ſad Thoughts one to the other, as they mov'd along the Shoar, and engaged in this lamentable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, weeping their Fate, without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, or conſideration, they had ſtragled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a Mile from the place where they firſt Landed, there they found an eaſie aſcent up the Mountains, 'twas a Path that was le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell'd as much as thoſe impregnable Rocks would permit, and appeared to be frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; they were in great diſpute, Whether they ſhould make any Sally alone, not only for fear of the Dangers they might encour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; but for fear of miſſing thoſe who had promiſed to bring them ſuccour, at laſt they reſolved to take a view of the Countries on the other ſide, and then to return to their appointed place, they fortified one another with Counſel, Courage and Comfort, and attained to the utmoſt height of the Clift, before they could think of deſcending, and to their great ſatisfaction, they found on that ſide an eaſie deſcent; they were like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe delighted with the pleaſant Proſpect of a lovely Champion Country ſtock'd with curious Rivers, and fine Woods; this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect for ſome time took up their Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and they had not yet determined what
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:151240:32"/>to do, when they heard the agreeable ſound of ſoft Muſick in a Wood, at the Foot of that Rock; they were now in hopes they were not far from Inhabitants, and believed it the beſt prudence to ſeek for ſhelter there, rather than truſt to poor famiſhed Wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, who perhaps were as far from Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort as ever; they made no longer delay, but with ſpeed deſcended, enter'd the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Wood, and made up, as nigh as they could gueſs, to the harmonious found that they heard on the Rock; they had not gone far before they came under the Shade of a Noble Poplar, which ſpread his Branches o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo large a Circumference, that it requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red admiration, as a curious piece of Nature; but what was more ſurpriſing to them, was to read on this Tree carved in great Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters on the Bark, <hi>Cruel <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nkind</hi> Octavio. This Name had dreadful effects on <hi>Don Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio,</hi> which made <hi>Carlo</hi> take pains to draw him from that place, leaſt it ſhould have proved prejudicial to them both; yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he would conſent to depart, he wrote underneath it with the point of his Sword, <hi>Cruel <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nkind</hi> Melantius. By this time the Muſick deſiſted, which put them to ſome trouble to find the way, but following a ſmall Track they had diſcovered, e're they were aware, they were entertained with the ſame Inſtrument again; and a Voice that
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:151240:32"/>was ſweet, and ſo nigh that it ſurpriſed them.</p>
            <p>The Words that were Sung, were theſe.</p>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>I.</head>
               <l>M<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſt I Love, and muſt I Languiſh,</l>
               <l>And ne'r hope to eaſe my Pain?</l>
               <l>Can I bear the bitter Anguiſh</l>
               <l>Of a ſlighted cold Diſdain?</l>
               <l>Is the Darts then of no power</l>
               <l>For to wound this Dear Ingrate?</l>
               <l>Muſt I ſuffer every Hour,</l>
               <l>And be pity'd when too late?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>Cruel God now change thy Faſhion,</l>
               <l>Since we muſt thy Will obey;</l>
               <l>Give us both an equal Paſſion,</l>
               <l>Or both Flames do thou allay:</l>
               <l>Say Great Deity, Muſt never</l>
               <l>My ſoft Wiſhes have redreſs?</l>
               <l>Oh! How vain is all endeavour?</l>
               <l>Love can only Love expreſs.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>They liſtned with great Attention, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving at the ſame time the advantage of ſeeing the lovely Perſon, who deliverd 'em in <hi>French,</hi> which both of them underſtood perfectly well; it being generally uſed by the Quality of moſt Nations: The Words were deliver'd with an Air all Paſſionate yet Serene; which <hi>Don Lelio</hi> had the ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:151240:33"/>of obſerving without being diſcover'd himſelf. The Youth appear'd about the Age of Sixteen, Beautiful as <hi>Narciſſus,</hi> Fair as the God of Love, his Eyes of the niceſt black, had a gloſs that out ſhined the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Day, and all his Features ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſingly perfect: He was dreſs'd after the <hi>French</hi> Mode, gallant in all things: His Hair which was curiouſly fair, was tied up in a Scarlet Ribbon: He was ſeated under a Myrtle Tree, and had a Lute under his Arm which afforded them this delightful Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. Appearing in this poſture, he exceeded all the Fictions that Poets attribute to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Woods, the Groves, the pleaſant murmuring noiſe of little Rivulets, and this amorous Song, gave <hi>Don Lelio</hi> a ſweet Idea of <hi>Elyzium;</hi> and it was no ſmall comfort to him, that his Fortune had caſt him on a Shoar where there were Lovers; he could not believe them a barbarous People, that were capable of ſo refin'd a Sentiment. The Verſes were ſo compoſed, they gave no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence, Whether a Man or Woman was complain'd of, and the Habit being all that appear'd Maſculine in this Charming Youth, who had ſo much Goodneſs, Innocence and Sweetneſs in his Looks, that they apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no danger to encounter him: When the Song ended, they made up to the place
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:151240:33"/>where he was, who appear'd in a great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order at their approach, but they being willing to put an end to a Fright (that had ſpread an agreeable Bluſh throughout his Face) readily told their Diſtreſs, declaring they were Shipwrackt Perſons, thrown by Fortune on that Coaſt, tho' diſtant from thence ſome Miles; the reſt of their Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny making their way over the dreadful Mountains, they only were left without hopes (unable to follow ſuch deſperate At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts) till their wandering Steps had led them to that place, which had an Eye of Humanity in it. They humbly intreated him to inform them where they might hope for ſome Relief. <hi>Don Arioſto</hi> (ſo was this young Cavalier call'd) viewing the effemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Delicacy of <hi>Don Lelio</hi> and his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rade, had pretty well diſſipated the Fears that had aſſaulted him, and being of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate tender Diſpoſition, was impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to aſſiſt them; therefore with a quick return, he requires them to follow him, and to his utmoſt endeavour he would contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to ſerve them, tho' he fear'd, the place could not produce any Accommodati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on worthy of ſuch Perſons; being acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with nothing but a poor Cabbin at the entrance of that Wood. They gladly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted the Favour, and full of grateful Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgments, redoubled their Paces to
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:151240:34"/>this happy Retreat, which they found mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable poor to appearance, but 'twas no ſmall Surprize to them when they entred, to ſee all things, tho' far from fine, curiouſly neat. The Inhabitants were, an Old Man, and an Old Woman, with one only Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, they received him with all the Joy in the World, and he appear'd to have no ſmall Authority there: Having firſt refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Strangers, with wholſome Cordials, he led them into a Room, where there was a little Field Bed, and all things elſe neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for a Cavalier, not to be expected in ſo mean a Manſion. He told them it had been his Abode a conſiderable time, finding more Content there, then in greater Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour. He preſented them Cloaths to ſhift themſelves, retiring that they might have liberty, whilſt he ordered a plentiful Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; at which he had a Relation of all their Misfortunes at Sea. This Entertainment was comfortable and delightful, but broke up ſoon, that the weary Travellers might take Repoſe after their hard Sufferings. How terrible was the Complement expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed here from <hi>Don Lelio?</hi> For it was but rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable he ſhould Invite <hi>Don Arioſto</hi> to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take a Lodging in his own Bed, whilſt the others oppoſing it, ſeem'd a gentle Courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, taking up with <hi>Cloe</hi>'s Chamber, who for a ſhift was forc'd to lye at the Feet of her Old Parents.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:151240:34"/>Our Adventurers ſpent ſome part of the Night in diſcourſing of their Deliverance, as alſo of the Youth, Beauty, and particular way of living of the Lovely <hi>Arioſto:</hi> And notwithſtanding ſome Sleep they had got, <hi>Don Lelio</hi> found himſelf the next Morning in a violent Feaver, unable to ſuſtain ſo hard a Fatigue, which whilſt his Body was in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitation he was inſenſible of. This News was a great Affliction to <hi>Don Arioſto,</hi> who uſed all Endeavours to reſtore his Health, he watch'd by him Night and Day, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred ſeveral things to him, having ſome knowledge in Phyſick, which Art he had for ſome time ſtudied; but finding his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines and his Care ineffectual, he was infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely concern'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Don Lelio</hi> continued deſperately ill, even to the threatning of his Life; yet during all this Sickneſs, not one had the leaſt Suſpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Sex; till one Day <hi>Carlo</hi> and he, whoſe conſtant Entertainment it was to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dole their ſad Deſtiny, had been ſeriouſly engaged in Diſcourſe, when upon ſome oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion <hi>Carlo</hi> quitted the Room, without warning, and that ſo ſoftly, he was not miſſed. Immediately enters <hi>Don Arioſto,</hi> and approached the Bed, but finding all ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and the ſick Cavalier's Head turn'd on the other ſide, concluding him aſleep, was juſt retiring, but was ſtopt by his Voice,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:151240:35"/>who believing he was ſtill ſpeaking to his faithful <hi>Carlo,</hi> thus went on: <hi>Ah!</hi> Laura, <hi>how imprudent will your poor Miſtreſs be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, for leaving an indulgent Father, and all the Glories of this World, to bear this Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and to purſue an unworthy falſe Ingrate, quit a Palace worthy of a King, to die here in a lonely Cott? But more, my dearest</hi> Laura, <hi>how terrible must</hi> Aſpatia's <hi>Memory be to thee, when thou dost reflect, that by her wild Conduct thou wert lost, left on a Forreign Shoar deſtitute of Friends; whilst thy weak Sex not dole to contend with the lean Jaws of Famine, Cold and miſerably Poor, perhaps ſome broken Crums for a</hi> Regalio, <hi>a Bed of Straw to reſt on, thy Sleep diſturbed with Fears, thy Days with Horrour, till by this lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gring Wretchedneſs you periſh. Canst thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give me then? Oh never! never!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This pitiful Complaint, not only fill'd <hi>Don Arioſto</hi> with Wonder, but with the moſt ſenſible Compaſſion imaginable, when <hi>Don Lelio</hi> who had deſiſted a while from ſpeaking, and hearing no reply, turn'd his languiſhing Eyes, which were drown'd in Tears to ſeek <hi>Carlo;</hi> but how full of confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion were thoſe Eyes to ſee <hi>Don Arioſto</hi> at the Bed-ſide? Fixt and immoveable he lay, and ſeem'd loſt in concern for what he had uttered: For ſometime <hi>Don Arioſto</hi> took pleaſure to gaze on her pretty Diſorder,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:151240:35"/>whilſt the other was tormented with a Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of Fears and Doubts; till Pity could no longer view ſuch cruel Sufferings, he ſtep'd up to her Bed, and with a Voice full of Amazement: <hi>Madam,</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>for ſo I now may call you, ſince Chance has made me your accidental Confident; I here ſtand ready to confirm with the most ſacred Vow, an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Secrecy; for it would be more then bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous in me, to inſult where all Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ought to oblige me to the tendereſt Compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; and therefore not to keep you longer in ſuſpence, and to ſecure you from all Fears or Jealouſies of me, know your Fortune has not play'd the moſt Jilting Game in caſting you on this deſpicable Shoar; for this Habit</hi> (point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to himſelf) <hi>conceals the ſame Sex.</hi> How incredible ſoever this appear'd to <hi>Don Lelio</hi> at firſt, his ſudden. Recovery from his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Confuſion, and the new Life it ſeem'd to inſpire him with, ſhew'd how willing he was to believe it; whilſt <hi>Don Arioſto</hi> thus continued: <hi>By what I have heard, Love has had a powerful Influence over you, which dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly engages me to ſerve you, for I bluſh not to own, I now ſuffer under the Extremity of that Paſſion.</hi> A great deal more he ſpoke to this purpoſe, giving convincing Proofs of what he ſaid. <hi>Don Lelio</hi> conceived no Bounds to his Joy at this Confeſſion; yet not being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſpeak till a multitude of intruding
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:151240:36"/>Sighs had made way, it was viſibly ſeen how timerouſly he entertained this happy Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very; at laſt with a faint Voice, between Hope and Diſtruſt he thus broke ſilence: <hi>With what Phraſe may I term you? Pardon my Diſpute, for I was ever difident of my own good Fortune, being almoſt inured to an unkind Deſtiny, but it would be no other than a Poor, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngenerous part in me, to Conceal any thing from a Perſon that ſo frankly has diſperſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my Fears, by a kind and free Declaration. I have no ſcruple now to confeſs to you ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, not only my Sex, but even all the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of my Life, when my Condition will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, and you are at leiſure to hear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As theſe words were delivering, <hi>Carlo</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered the Room, in no ſmall Surprize (as may be imagined) which was much more augmented to hear <hi>Don Lelio,</hi> call (in a free and unconcern'd manner) by the Name of <hi>Laura,</hi> taking <hi>Don Arioſto</hi> by the Hand, and thus ſpeaking: <hi>My poor</hi> Laura, <hi>how much am I bound to Heaven, that in mittiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my deplorable Diſaſters, has rais'd me here the beſt of Friends, and one whoſe Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings ſtrangely ſympathize with mine. Fear not to imbrace with the tendereſt Affection this our Generous Protector, for the Charming</hi> Arioſto <hi>is a Woman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:151240:36"/>Wonder and Amazement crowded thick upon <hi>Carlo,</hi> to find ſo ſtrange a Revolution in ſo ſhort a ſpace; but being confirm'd by the Mouth of Don <hi>Arioſto</hi> all that had paſs'd, ſhe was overjoy'd: with unſpeakable ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction did theſe metamorphos'd Fair Ones unite; and having ſpent ſome time in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing of ſmall Occurrences of their Lifes, they declin'd the principal Events to a more favourable opportunity, that the recital might not be troubleſome or tedious to Don <hi>Lelio.</hi> For that night they parted infinitely pleas'd, and with ſuch mutual Engagements of Friendſhip and Fidelity, that none could be greater or more ſubſtantial.</p>
            <p>From this moment Don <hi>Lelio</hi> recover'd, ſo much doth the Satisfaction of the Mind contribute to the Health of the Body, in a ſhort time he became perfectly well: But during his Sickneſs, which laſted Eight Months, you ſhall have an account of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantius,</hi> whom we left in the <hi>Florentines</hi> Army.</p>
            <p>To tell, with advantage, the wonderful and glorious Exploits of that young <hi>Hero,</hi> would be too mighty a Subject to joyn with this Trifle; nor ought a leſs florid Pen than that of <hi>Homer,</hi> or <hi>Virgil,</hi> undertake ſo heroick a Task; therefore let it ſuffice, that after having perform'd beyond the Credulity of Man, it was his chance, during a Truce, to
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:151240:37"/>be ſent with other Commanders, to recruit their Troops with <hi>Neapolitans,</hi> having Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from the State. They arriv'd at <hi>Naples</hi> about the time of Don <hi>Lelio</hi>'s reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, and had march'd thro' the remoteſt parts of that Republick, in queſt of Men, which they imagin'd might hide themſelves in thoſe Mountains, to avoid a Service at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with too many Hazards. They were now within a league of that ſacred Wood which harbour'd the lovely unfortunate Don <hi>Lelio.</hi> This place <hi>Melantius</hi> had already found out, where he often ſought to calm and ſweeten the Frenzy of his Mind, which was almoſt feſter'd by Deſpair.</p>
            <p>One day he had retir'd hither, to ſeek a Sanctuary in the midſt of Solitude; when ſtriving to ſhake off his oppreſſing Fetters, he was convinc'd there was no evading the Sentence of the Deity, and therefore reſign'd himſelf up as Love's cruel Martyr, and not without a harſh Conteſt betwixt Love and Honour. This Debate held him till he ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd, all hopeleſs, at the foot of the Poplar (we ſpoke of) whoſe beauty and exceeding largeneſs took up his conſideration ſome ſmall time; but when he eſpied thoſe two Senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces on the Bark, writ in different Characters, who can deſcribe his Confuſion! oppreſs'd with a heavy weight of Fears, Doubts, and Jealouſie, he was hardly able to ſupport his
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:151240:37"/>ſinking Fate. The Blood came thrilling from his panting Heart, his Sinews ſhrunk, and ſo ſtrange a Lethargy came all over his fainting Senſes, that he ſeem'd fix'd to the center, at length, with hard ſtrugling to reſiſt this powerful Charm, he regain'd his Spirits, but ſo faint and weak, he was forced to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, and leave the purſuit of this Myſtery till the morrow. But inſtead of reſt that night, his dark melancholy Thoughts were fill'd with Illuſions and Fancies, as perplexing as thoſe he came from.</p>
            <p>The next morning, which was one of the ſereneſt and pleaſanteſt imaginable, he was up with the firſt ſummons of the chirping Lark, and with greedy and thoughtful ſteps travers'd the enamel'd Fields, till he enter'd the Wood, where he began a curious ſearch, examining every Tree, if poſſible, to make a farther diſcovery. He met with ſeveral little Sentences, but no more intelligible than the other; being come under the ſhady embracing greens of that proud Poplar, where he, the day before he was ſeiz'd with that anxious Trouble, had ſome Reflections on the hard meaſure of his Tyrannick Chains, but overcame them with a Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to continue his ſearch.</p>
            <p>He had not advanc'd far, but there pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to his Eyes two young beautiful Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valiers, Arm in Arm, walking a deliberate
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:151240:38"/>pace; and one at ſome diſtance behind them. Theſe were the reciprocal and charming Don <hi>Lelio,</hi> Don <hi>Arioſto,</hi> and <hi>Carlo,</hi> who had choſe this lovely Morn to eaſe the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets and Burden of their Souls. They ſeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves on the Bank of a pleaſant and purling Stream, ſo cloſe to the place where <hi>Melantius</hi> had conceal'd himſelf, that with eaſe he overheard all they ſaid.</p>
            <p>The firſt that broke ſilence was Don <hi>Arioſto,</hi> who, after ſome deliberation, thus began:</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="history">
                        <head>The Hiſtory of <hi>Canace.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>THE Story which I ſhall tell you will be brief, having no Adventure to entertain your Ears, but the unaccountable Paſſion of a fooliſh and credulous Woman.</p>
                        <p>My Birth, without oſtentation, is as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable as any Family this day in <hi>Italy,</hi> being Daughter of the Marqueſs <hi>de Caſtigli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one Della Stivere,</hi> who married one of the Illuſtrious Houſe of <hi>Caraffa</hi> in <hi>Naples;</hi> their Hearts were firmly united, and for ſome few years enjoy'd the calmeſt Sererity that a tender Paſſion, attended with Greatneſs and Plenty, could create: But Love, nor
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:151240:38"/>all this Tranquility, could not defend them from the Tyrannick Power of Death; for, my Mother, after being deliver'd of me her fatal Offspring, at the end of thirteen months reſign'd her Charms to the cold Tomb, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Marqueſs my Father the moſt deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of Men; which he gave evident de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of to the World, not being able to ſurvive the dear Partner of his ſofter hours full three months.</p>
                        <p>My Parents being dead, I was committed to the charge of the Viſcount <hi>Bozzolos,</hi> the noble and reciprocal Friend of my deceaſed Father, who in particular had left me his Ward, where I was brought up by the Viſcounteſs (his Lady) with all the care imaginable, till maturer years made me ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of the beſt Education, which was li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berally beſtow'd upon me. But ill Fortune ſtill attended me, and bereft me a ſecond time of an affectionate Mother: 'Twas a Loſs difficultly to be ſupported by the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſolate Viſcount; yet Time wearing out the Exceſs of his Sorrow, he began to be comforted in the blooming Virtues of one only Son, and me, now his adopted Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in whom every little Advantage of Wit and Beauty was his Glory. I was now the abſolute Miſtreſs of his Houſe, and ſo equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly did he ſhare his Favours between <hi>Octavio</hi> (ſo was his Son call'd) and me, that the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:151240:39"/>niceſt Eye could not judge which ſtood fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in his Affections. Yet an unkind turn of Fortune render'd us two the ingrateful In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of his Affliction; for, our Infant Natures, which had made us Companions in our harmleſs Pleaſures, united us in a ſtrong Band of Friendſhip, which daily improving, as we ripen'd in years, at length produced a mighty flame: Not that this could have done us any prejudice of itſelf, being (as we underſtood after) what the Viſcount ever wiſhed: but not knowing how it would be accepted of, (and a timerous baſhfulneſs that generally attends young Lovers) made us induſtrious to conceal a Paſſion which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently prov'd my Ruine.</p>
                        <p>Joyn'd to <hi>Octavio</hi>'s Virtue, Wit, and Beauty, he had all the Power and Art of fine Perſwaſion; noble, facetious, and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, but juſter to his Friendſhip than his Love; one who could never fail to make his Paſſion proſper; with ſuch Inſinuation would he move, none could reſiſt his Whiſpers and Addreſs. In ſhort, he made a Conqueſt of <hi>Canace,</hi> turn'd me to what he wiſh'd; he won my Soul with honourable Vows, and for my Love return'd me double Intereſt. Thus, for ſome years, we enjoy'd a calm Content of ſecret, innocent, and virtuous Friendſhip. Wrap'd in theſe chaſt Delights, we never once had Dreams of greater Bliſs,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:151240:39"/>had not the revolution of Affairs convinc'd us, that a Lover's Hopes has no Confine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Octavio,</hi> to be render'd more polite, being already Maſter of his Studies, was by his Father ſent to read the World and Men.</p>
                        <p>This Separation was a fatal blow, to two united with an ardent Paſſion; but, being limited to juſt three years, we ſtrove to bear it with a handſom courage, not part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without mutual Proteſtations of Love, Fidelity, of Truth and all. Here Paſſion ſwell'd ſo big ſhe could not ſpeak, and fill'd her Auditors with feeling pity. But a few Sighs being paſt, and having dried her love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Eyes, ſhe renew'd her Diſcourſe, where 'twas broke off, and all that laviſh Wiſhes could ſuggeſt, to Hearts then flaming with a pure Deſire.</p>
                        <p>His Travels being accompanied with a noble Youth, the Confidant and Friend of all his Pleaſures, (by Name <hi>Alcidas,</hi> of the great Family of <hi>Pittis,</hi> thoſe mighty Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitors to the Houſe of <hi>Medicis,</hi> whoſe En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity has been ſo long contracted, that the colateral Branches of that Houſe ſtill bear the unjuſt Reſentment of that Quarrel;) ſome minutes ſtole away without Regret; my Faith I plighted, and he ſwore to be for ever mine. But, oh! forgive my interrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sighs, Who can relate the fickle Chance
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:151240:40"/>of Fortune, without grief, which more is to be blam'd than any breach of my <hi>Octavio</hi>'s Promiſe?</p>
                        <p>A conſtant correſpondence paſs'd between us; and that we might with freedom write our Thoughts, our Letters were directed to one had been my Servant, who being now diſpos'd of in the World, liv'd ſtill with grateful Sentiments to ſerve me.</p>
                        <p>Having thus paſſed two Year, and better, my cruel Fate drew on apace,</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Alcidas</hi>'s buſineſs call'd him home in haſte, when having made all ready for his Journey, <hi>Octavio</hi> recommended to his care, Letters to his Father, and to me. He was no Stranger to our conſtant Vows; <hi>Octavio</hi> had impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all that paſs'd, and left him as the truſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of his Friends, with Juſtice to applaud his Love and Virtue. But ſee the ſtrange reverſe of Fortune, <hi>Alcidas</hi> came full fraught from poor <hi>Octavio,</hi> with Love, freſh Vows, and a thouſand fond Addreſſes; which he defers to a kind opportunity, diſpatching firſt his buſineſs to the State. He now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a conſtant Viſiter, entertaining us with Stories of <hi>Octavio;</hi> the great delight I took in hearing of him, made me ne'r fail to be in company; yet no ſecure occaſion did preſent, to make me happy with that dear Epiſtle. My <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>rm attention, when he did diſplay the Courage, Wit, and Beauty of
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:151240:40"/>my Lover, engag'd my Heart, my Ears, my Eyes upon him; but, oh! how often have I been ſurpriz'd to find his Colour come and go, his Speech to faulter, with all the ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptoms of a troubled Mind. This paſs'd without my knowing what it meant, being reſolv'd not to take notice of it; but yet, alas! too ſoon I knew the Cauſe. <hi>Alcidas</hi> being frequent in his viſits, came on a day the Viſcount was abroad; I entertain'd him with an eaſie Freedom, but the ungenerous Paſſion raging in his Breaſt, made him remiſs in all the Gallantries he did obſerve, he look'd wild, turn'd pale, and anſwer'd, <hi>Mal a Propos,</hi> to all I ſpoke, ſeeming involv'd in anxious Cares and Trouble.</p>
                        <p>I knew not what to think, but fear'd the worſt, and was juſt going to ask him his Diſeaſe, when I percerv'd him riſe, and come towards me trembling, he held a Letter in his Hand, his Eyes half drown'd in Tears, he had not power to ſpeak, till a large ſhower was ſprinkled at my Feet, then in the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of an humble Supplicant, he thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan:</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Madam, you ſee here proſtrate at your feet one whom the Fates have done their worſt to plague. The envious Gods throw heavy Curſes on me, and rend my Soul with Horrour and with Death. I from my youth have been</hi>
                           <pb n="68" facs="tcp:151240:41"/>Octavio'<hi>s Friend, his ſecret, conſtant, honeſt, boſom Friend, lov'd where he lov'd, contemn'd where he deſpis'd, affected all Diverſions he approv'd, loath'd Place and Perſon that he did not like: So equally, ſo firm, ſo true we lov'd, as we were made to pleaſure one another. What ſhall I ſay? The Heavens have done their worſt to make a Wretch of baſe undone</hi> Alci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das; <hi>this Friend, that dar'd to trust me with his Life, made me the Confidant to your A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, and recommended to my faithful charge Ten thouſand tender Vows, and paſſionate Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes, withal this Letter,</hi> (putting in my Hand the Billet which he held, but ſtill went on) <hi>which I diſcharge, as I am bound by Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. But, oh! when making to this happy Soil, why was I not blaſted on the way, drown'd in the turbulent, rude, boisterous Floods, or ſhook by ſome rough Thunderbolt to Atomes? Then Friends might ſay,</hi> So fell juſt good <hi>Alcidas. But I must live to loſe my Fame and Value, and dye a Blot and Scandal to my Name. Curſed be thoſe Stars that did conduct me to thoſe Charms which made a Captive of my Friend</hi> Octavio; <hi>my Opticks are the ſame, my Heart is his, and where he loves, I cannot but adore. Then pardon, Madam, that you here behold your Slave re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd to love, without a Limit.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="69" facs="tcp:151240:41"/>Here having ſtop'd, I knew not what to ſay: I muſt confeſs, I felt a great Compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, his modeſt Speech could not incurr my Anger; his ſenſe of Wrongs and Faults com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted pleas'd me; and I commiſerating his ill chance, was going to return, when he proceeded:</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Judge, Madam, the ſad Conflict of my Heart, betwixt my Love and thoſe most ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Ties of Friendſhip. Muſt I then wrong my Friend? By all that's good, I will not play him falſe.</hi> And at theſe words he ſtarted up in haſte, his Words and Geſture ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much reſolv'd, when ſuddenly his Ayre was wholly chang'd, and falling faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at my Feet again; <hi>But, oh!</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>my Heart is not my own; who can reſist thoſe Charms I now behold?</hi> And ſaying ſo, his Spirit ſunk within him, and left him breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs by me on the Floor.</p>
                        <p>This Accident indeed diſturb'd me much, I call'd for the Aſſiſtance of my Maid, and with our Induſtry and Care recover'd him. Then I began to plead againſt his Paſſion, to repreſent my Contract to <hi>Octavio;</hi> ſtill taking care to clinch upon his Honour, and blow thoſe noble Sparks I ſtill felt warm with Generoſity, which I affirm'd would render him more Praiſe, more Joy, than the fruition of my dull Embraces: He heard with all the torment of Deſpair; yet being
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:151240:42"/>byaſs'd by his generous Genius, he did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to quit the Siege, and never, never more to ſee my Face; but parting, told me, when I heard his Death, which ſuddenly would invade my Ears, I ſhould remember, none ever lov'd ſo well, nor none e'er ſuffer'd more.</p>
                        <p>In ſhort, he ſeem'd fix'd in his Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which fill'd me with a World of Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, hoping that Abſence might effect his Cure, without that cruel Remedy of Death. I retir'd with a Mind tranſported with the Thoughts of my <hi>Octavio,</hi> read his dear Letter over twenty times, kiſs'd and careſs'd his Characters and Seal, and thought my ſelf ſecure from this <hi>Alcidas.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>But ſee the frailty of a Lover's Promiſe: 'Tis true, he made no more his common Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits, endeavouring with true care to avoid my preſence; but the croſs Deſtinies, that ow'd us Spight, led his dull penſive Steps in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Church where I was offering up my Hours Devotions: He came up to the Altar where I kneel'd, and plac'd himſelf a little diſtance from me, but knew me not, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of my Veil: Nor had I yet obſerv'd a Man ſo near me; for being wrap'd in a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphick Joy, my Thoughts had no relation to the World; when flinging up my Veil, to breath ſome Air, I heard the Voice of one in great ſurprize cry out, <hi>Good God, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:151240:42"/>me;</hi> with that I turn'd, and to my troubled view appear'd <hi>Alcidas,</hi> pale as Death, unable to ſupport his ſinking Limbs, his Eyes all languiſhing with Love and Pain, ſpoke with more moving Rhetorick than a Tongue; yet, Pity being all I could afford, I left him in that moſt deplorable eſtate, whilſt he, without the power to move my ſtay, made faint Petitions with his trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling Hands; but I, deaf and inſenſible as the Winds, fled, and with eager paces got me home, where I began to exclaim againſt this Chance, with angry reſentment of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidas.</hi> How much he lov'd, I was too well convinc'd, and doubted the Event of ſuch a Paſſion: I plainly ſaw how Willingly he ſtrove, with Violence and Art, to quench his Flame, but yet the gnawing Tortures of his Breaſt inſenſibly excites him to relief: Two or three Interviews he got of me, fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his ſoft Fire into a furious Blaze, which he no longer able to ſupport, abandon'd <hi>Friendſhip, Honour, Truth,</hi> and <hi>Virtue,</hi> and gave himſelf intirely up to <hi>Love.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The firſt Advance he put in execution, was, to propoſe our Marriage to the <hi>Viſcount,</hi> which ſeveral times was done without my Knowledge. The aged Seniors met in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation, and ſtruck the Bargain as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves thought fit. <hi>Alcidas</hi>'s Family was rich and noble, himſelf admir'd for a gallant
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:151240:43"/>Youth, lov'd, valu'd, and approv'd of by the World; which pleas'd the <hi>Viſcount,</hi> that I there ſhould match, to Honour, and to Wealth, as I was born.</p>
                        <p>Things being thus decreed, 'twas requiſite next to conſult my Mind in this Affair, of which I had not entertain'd the leaſt Suſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; till on a day, penſive, and ſad as Death, I choſe the Garden for a ſafe retreat, to nurſe that melancholy vapour which op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd me. After I had ſpent ſome time in troubled Thoughts, under the ſhady Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the Trees, my Maid drew near, and gave to me a Letter; the Character I had never ſeen before, which ſeiz'd me with a ſtrange unuſual Diſtruſt; but when I open'd it, and found <hi>Alcidas</hi>'s Name, Gods! how it ſtruck me with a killing Fear! my feeble Limbs could hardly do their Office, to bear me to a little private Arbour, where I ſate down to read the fatal Billet; the Contents thereof were theſe:</p>
                        <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <head>ALCIDAS <hi>to</hi> CANACE.</head>
                              <p>LOVE, the predominant Paſſion of the Mind, I find, can bear with no Competi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor; how much I have strove to overcome its Power, witneſs thou great Controuler of our Reaſon: but the reſiſtleſs Charms of Heaven-born Beauty has quite caſhier'd that idle No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:151240:43"/>
                                 <hi>Honour,</hi> which ſerves but to betray our free-born Wiſhes to the Capricio of another's Appetite; a meer fantaſtick empty Vanity of our own making, and govern'd by our Wills, not Inclinations. <hi>Octavio</hi> loves, but much more doth <hi>Alcidas:</hi> Deſire doth rage in every vital part; nor can my Soul ſubſiſt without your Pity: I can no longer ſuffer endleſs pains, Nature will prompt us Remedies to ſeek, and Reaſon teach us how to eaſe a Torment. Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der not, Madam, that I have engag'd the Viſcount's Pleaſure, to ſecure you mine; all that can move an Avaricious Mind, ſhall la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhly be offer'd at your Feet; only reſolve to make me truly happy, ſince my unbounded Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion will aſpire to gratifie the tenderest of my Thoughts, and proſecute with vigour my De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, being poſitively deſtin'd ever Yours,</p>
                              <closer>
                                 <signed>ALCIDAS.</signed>
                              </closer>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                        <p>I found by this, his Hopes were much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted; the Viſcount's Promiſe ſtrangely did amaze me, for yet he had not told me his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, nor did I dream I was ſo near a Ruine; what ſhould be done, I could no way determine, but ſate confounded at this cruel blow. When I perceiv'd the Viſcount paſs me by, a thouſand Reſolutions fill'd my Mind, which ſuddenly were loſt without Concluſion: Sometimes I thought to charge him with Injuſtice, blame his too free di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſal
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:151240:44"/>of my Heart, and poſitively refuſe the Match. When milder Thoughts took place, I ſoon found this too raſh; Honour and Virtue bound me ſtill to Duty, ſince he had prov'd in all reſpects a Father: to tell him how <hi>Octavio</hi> and I lov'd, could no way get admittance from my Tongue; and Reaſon did ſuggeſt, that had he liked that Love, he would have firſt propos'd it.</p>
                        <p>Debates and Tumults riſing in my Breaſt, I knew no Method how I ſhould allay them. Oppreſs'd without the comfort of Relief, various Opinions ended in this laſt, of tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him with an unkind proceeding: With that I quit the Arbour where I ſate, and met the Viſcount, who was now return'd. My Thoughts ſwell'd high to vent a Flood of Grief, but a reſpectful Awe confin'd my Tongue, and I had no more power left than juſt to ask him of his Health: However, long I was not in ſuſpence; the Viſcount fondly told me his Deſign, bid me prepare to make a happy Bride, and bleſs the World with an Illuſtrious Offspring. He told me, I muſt wed the brave <hi>Alcidas,</hi> with all the Advantages that Fate could give, or I could wiſh for. What I return'd I cannot now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; my Thoughts were ſo diſturb'd, I quite forgot my Anſwer, but ſure I am I very much oppos'd it, which he imply'd to
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:151240:44"/>Virgin-Modeſty, bidding me depart, and wiſely make my Choice.</p>
                        <p>I left him almoſt ready to expire, got to my Chamber, where I wrote at large each circumſtance and tittle to <hi>Octavio,</hi> bid him make haſte to ſave a conſtant Maid, ſince Life or Death depended on his ſtay; but not a Letter ever reach'd his Hands, <hi>Alcidas</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercepted all that paſs'd, ſtill puſhing on with violence and care the conſummation of a wretched Bliſs.</p>
                        <p>Hard ſhift I made to get two months Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieve, in hopes to have an Anſwer from <hi>Octavio,</hi> but ſeeing none, I found there was a Cheat; Rage and Reſentment ſo poſſeſs'd my Mind, I gave myſelf up wholly to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair, and did at the laſt extremity reſolve to ſacrifice myſelf when at the Altar. Things were now almoſt brought to a concluſion, the Wedding-day prefix'd, a Pomp prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, where I was to ſurrender by compulſion a Hand, where I could not reſign a Heart: but what prevented my unhappy fall, kills my ſad Soul with the remembrance: <hi>Octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vio,</hi> by ſome baſe officious Hand, had falſe Intelligence of this Amour, wherein they repreſented it my Choice, with all the ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravations could incenſe a man abus'd, as he believ'd he was: The Viſcount's Letters told him of our Marriage, without the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of my averſion, and ne'er receiving
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:151240:45"/>any one from me, confirm'd him eaſily, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond diſpute, that I was turn'd a fickle mean Ingrate.</p>
                        <p>What he deſign'd I never yet could learn, but he with ſpeed came poſting home to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drid,</hi> a place where we for many years re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſided, enter'd the City privately at night, and got admittance in the Family; 'twas late, and we were all retired to Reſt, which made him give Command not to diſturb us; but no Repoſe could eaſe my weary Eyes, that almoſt were conſum'd with Tears and Grief. I ſpent that night in Tortures be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Wracks, dreading each moment which drew on the day when I was to be married to <hi>Alcidas.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>This News <hi>Octavio</hi> learnt in his Diſcourſe with an old Servant, that had let him in, which raiſed him to the heighth of Deſpara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Some hours he trac'd the Room in great diſorder, having difmiſs'd the Servant to his Bed, with charge to keep it ſecret he was there; whilſt bandying in his Thoughts Ten thouſand Projects, ill Chance, and not Premeditation, forc'd an Act, which Love, and only Love, muſt juſtifie.</p>
                        <p>Juſt as the Day peep'd thro' its thick Veil, and caſt imperfect Shadows on the Earth, <hi>Alcidas,</hi> whoſe tranſported Thoughts ne'r reſted, impatient of delay, came under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:151240:45"/>my Window, and with a gentle Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons rais'd his voice to theſe Expreſſions, which as my Maid took down, I well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member:</p>
                        <q>
                           <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                              <body>
                                 <div type="song">
                                    <head>The SONG.</head>
                                    <lg>
                                       <l>ASTREA, <hi>wake, diſperſe thy Fears;</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>Look up, behold, the Day appears:</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>Whilst I impatiently do wait,</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>The promis'd bliſs, to crown my Fate.</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>Phoebus, <hi>laſh on each fiery Steed,</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>Let</hi> Phaeton <hi>ſupply thy ſpeed;</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>My Heart does burn as well as bleed.</hi>
                                       </l>
                                    </lg>
                                    <lg>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>Riſe and outſhine the ſplendid Light;</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>Let every killing Grace invite,</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>And raiſe my Soul to ſuch deſire,</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>That Thought no farther can aſpire:</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>Then every dying Sigh ſhall breath</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>The Extaſie I do receive,</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>And thoſe Delights I mean to give.</hi>
                                       </l>
                                    </lg>
                                    <lg>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>Clear up thoſe gloomy drooping Eyes,</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>And ſee the glorious Sun ariſe,</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>With brighter Splendor to ſurvey</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>The Triumphs of this happy day:</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>Away with all diſdainful Pride,</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>All coy Reſerv'dneſs lay aſide;</hi>
                                       </l>
                                       <l>
                                          <hi>Prepare to be a joyful Bride.</hi>
                                       </l>
                                    </lg>
                                 </div>
                              </body>
                           </floatingText>
                        </q>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="78" facs="tcp:151240:46"/>
                           <hi>Octavio</hi> did with pain attend the end, and being well convinc'd this was <hi>Alcidas,</hi> ruſh'd out upon him in a Storm of Rage, and with a Dagger ſmiting in his Breaſt, cry'd out, <hi>This as a grateful Preſent from</hi> Canace, <hi>deliver'd by the Hands of wrong'd</hi> Octavio.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Alcidas</hi> ſtruggl'd with a weak defence, and ſtrove to gain ſome time to draw his Sword, but 'twas too late, the Wound he had receiv'd laid him on the Ground, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd of Life.</p>
                        <p>I from my Chamber plainly heard what paſſed, which render'd me half dead with Fear and Horrour; too well I knew <hi>Octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vio</hi>'s voice to be deceiv'd, and could not gueſs what Fate had brought him thither; a thouſand dreadful Thoughts did multiply, and fill'd my Boſom with a throbbing Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour: hurried by diſtracted Fears, I flung a Night-gown careleſly upon me, and ran with open Arms to find <hi>Octavio,</hi> but found him in a manner overwhelm'd with Sorrow. The lovely Mourner, fix'd as in a Trance, ſtood weeping o'er the Body of <hi>Alcidas,</hi> when I with trembling Tranſport ſeiz'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, ſpoke all the tenderneſs that Love could dictate, but he contemning all my Sighs and Tears, forced himſelf violently from my Arms, made no Reply to any thing I ſaid, but threw me from him with a ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:151240:46"/>Diſdain, and left my Heart juſt burſting with this uſage, whilſt he with nimble flight ſtole from the City, got to his Servant left without the Gates, mounted his Horſe, and rode for Life and Refuge, abandon'd by all Comfort to his Fortune.</p>
                        <p>Mad as a frantick <hi>Bacchanal</hi> I rav'd, and hardly could be hinder'd from purſuing him. My Maid had us'd all Arguments with Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that might perſwade a ſenſe not wholly baniſh'd; but finding I was refractory to Advice, and hearing the trampling noiſe of Feet draw near, made no Apology, but pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led me in, and gently ſhut the Door.</p>
                        <p>This Quarrel reach'd no Ears but only ours, except the Servant, who had let him in, who finding him uneaſie in his Mind, had modeſtly withdrawn to wait his Order, and accidentally being fallen aſleep, not waken'd till the Fray was almoſt over: Scarce had my Maid chain'd up the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Gate, but he approach'd us with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order'd Care, making a ſtrict Enquiry for <hi>Octavio;</hi> Oh! how I ſunk beneath my load of Fears, left this loved cruel Man ſhould now be ruin'd; Ingrateful as he was, I ſtill ador'd him: 'Twas then, even tho' his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries were freſh, I did forget the Outrage done my Heart, to think of Means for his Security: Stifling the Anguiſh of my ſinking Soul, I made a cunning ſearch into this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:151240:47"/>and learnt from him the time <hi>Octavio</hi> came, and that he was alone, diſguiſed and dull, that none had ſeen him enter but him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, whom Buſineſs accidentally had kept up. This gave, through all my Fears, ſome little Hope, that probably there might be no Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt, if I could bribe this man to Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crefie.</p>
                        <p>With ſubtile Inſtruments I prob'd his Breaſt, and found it at the bottom truly honeſt, his Intereſt and Advantage was <hi>Octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vio</hi>'s, whom he loved and ſerved for many Years, admir'd in Infancy his budding <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues,</hi> and at thoſe early days ſought his <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection;</hi> yet I not failed, from time to time, to ſeal his vow'd Fidelity with powerful Gold. Having thus paſſed a ſacred ſolemn Promiſe, next, to avoid Suſpition in the Houſe, we ſtole with ſilent Caution all to Bed, to me the moſt deteſted place in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (becauſe deſign'd for Reſt and Faſe); yet forc'd my Heart even far beyond my Will, ſince all this Care concern'd <hi>Octavio</hi>'s Good.</p>
                        <p>Till nine of the Clock the next morning, I ſuffer'd all the racking Pains of Love, Fear, and Jealouſie, and by this time Report was ſpread throughout the City, that <hi>Alcidas</hi> was ſlain, his Hat and Gloves, that drop'd in the Rencounter, being found drench'd in a dreadful gore of Blood, but for the Body,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:151240:47"/>it could not be heard of, tho' careful ſtrict enquiry was made. The Viſcount ſtartled at the fatal news, came trembling with ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize and grief, to tell me; at ſight of whom, before he ſpoke a word, Reflection daſh'd my tortur'd breaſt, and not being able to ſupport its weight, I ſunk from the Chair I ſate, into a Swoon. He gueſs'd, by this, that I had been inform'd, and weeping, bore a part in my Affliction, pitying my Loſs, and poor <hi>Alcidas</hi>'s Fortune. Induſtry was us'd to bring my Life, but all their Application was in vain, till above half the day was ſpent, then I began to breath the Air of wild Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction. <hi>Madrid</hi> was now the Seat of Wonder, Rage, and Sorrow; the Murder of ſo great a man was generally lamented: a ſearch was now began throughout the City, both for the Aſſaſſinates and wretched Corps, no Houſe, or Vault, or Well eſcap'd a ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſack, which gave me all the agony of Fear, for the unfortunate diſtreſs'd <hi>Octavio;</hi> yet all this diligence made no diſcovery, no Author found that had done ſuch a deed, nor could <hi>Alcidas</hi>'s Body e'er be heard of, which Riddle I could never underſtand. Our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily did ſuffer cruel Cenſures; my ſtrange Averſion, and the fatal Place, the Time, nay, every Circumſtance look'd odd, and gave too fair Pretences for Suſpicion, but nothing could be prov'd; ſo that the Death
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:151240:48"/>of this Unfortunate receiv'd no other expia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion than a publick Sorrow.</p>
                        <p>Contrary to my Hopes, 'tis true, I liv'd, but liv'd the moſt dejected She on Earth; mourn'd that this Tragedy was not my own, rather than be the Fate of all adored me: I ſaw the paſſionate <hi>Alcidas</hi> fall, and fear'd the utter loſs of brave <hi>Octavio;</hi> his parting Blow kept ſtill a freſh Idea of all the Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that there was acted. I doubted his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of Mind would prompt him raſhly to deſtroy himſelf; or, if he liv'd, he liv'd no longer mine. How wretched, how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy was my Life! my Fears augmented by perpetual Silence; no Tidings of <hi>Octavio</hi> could be heard, no Letter nor no Meſſage did come near us, which much perplexed the melancholy <hi>Viſcount;</hi> but I, that knew too much, and dreaded to know more, dy'd dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the expectation of the worſt. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times I thought I was oblig'd to ſpeak, that neceſſary Methods might be taken; but, oh! the Bloody Fact had ſo much Horror, that my Soul ſhrunk at the remembrance, to tell the <hi>Viſcount</hi> 'twas impoſſible, and likewiſe barbarous to diſturb his Peace; beſides, I knew not how he would reſent my manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in keeping it ſo long. Thus reſtleſs, thus oppreſs'd, I ſunk beneath the Burden of a Secret, which Time had made too dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to reveal. The ſmall Relief of Hope
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:151240:48"/>had almoſt left me: Silent and ſad, I bore a tedious Pain, and only waited Death to give me Eaſe, when there arriv'd a Letter from <hi>Octavio;</hi> the <hi>Viſcount,</hi> unto whom it was directed, read it with all the ſmiling Ayr of Pleaſure, but my prophetick Fear allow'd no Tranſport; an unaccountable foretelling Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs did overcome my Joy, to hear he liv'd; I dreaded to enquire, yet knew not why; but, oh! too ſoon the <hi>Viſcount</hi> did expoſe that Letter, which produc'd my final Ruin.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Octavio</hi> was now at <hi>Portugal,</hi> from whence he excuſed his long ſilence and ſtay, ſince 'twas not to be imagin'd he could return to <hi>Madrid,</hi> without endangering the loſs of Life and Fortune, for Reaſons which he gueſs'd the <hi>Viſcount</hi> knew; but he, good Man, did only apprehend theſe words as they related to the next that follow'd, which told him of a noble Match propos'd, between himſelf and a moſt glorious Maid, fram'd by peculiar Providence with care, and made a charming Abſtract of Perfection; <hi>Aſpatia,</hi> happy <hi>Aſpatia,</hi> was her Name, Daughter to the moſt Renowned Duke <hi>de Almeyda,</hi> born to command and conquer all that ſaw her: Crowds of adoring Slaves lay at her Feet, and gloried in their bleſt Captivity, the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe did ne'r produce before a clearer <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, Wit,</hi> or ſolid <hi>Judgment;</hi> nor Nature form ſo lovely or exact a <hi>Beauty; For, oh!</hi>
                           <pb n="84" facs="tcp:151240:49"/>(ſaid ſhe, in Sighs and floods of Tears) <hi>I have heard her perfect and impartial Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>At this Don <hi>Lelio</hi> bluſh'd, and almoſt died with ſwift reflections on his vanquiſh'd Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and the kind laviſh Praiſes of his Rival. The ſad conceal'd <hi>Melantius,</hi> at this part, was ready with his Paſſion to expire, but chaced with violence his Spleen away, to give attention to the mournful Sequel; whilſt Don <hi>Ariosto,</hi> who had too much Grief to mind an alteration in Don <hi>Lelio,</hi> proceeded in this manner:</p>
                        <p>'Twas here my Fugitive diſcover'd Charms; nor Sorrow, Wit, nor Reaſon coul withſtand; ſuch Charms, that when his Soul was all o'er dark and diſmal Horror calm'd and diſpers'd the melancholy Cloud, diſarm'd the torturing Fury in his Breaſt, and plac'd a Troop of ſmiling <hi>Cupids</hi> there; 'twas not without encouragement he wrote to learn what he might hope for from his Father, on what Demands he might expect to gain a Beauty of that bounteous Wit and Dower, giving his Raptures latitude to ſpeak the moſt he thought his Miſtreſs could deſerve.</p>
                        <p>This when I read, no Tongue can tell my ſmart, my throbbing Breaſt did heave, my Eyes diſtorted, no doubtful Wretch that ſtood their lateſt Doom, was half ſo ſhock'd
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:151240:49"/>at a condemning Sentence, ſpeechleſs and cold I fell upon the ground, and only ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breath'd Sighs declar'd I liv'd; but ſoon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain I did recover ſtrength, to fall a Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant at the Viſcount's Feet, to whom I wept, and told the movingſt Tale, that his ſad Preſſures, like to <hi>Niobe</hi>'s, ſeem'd to have turn'd his reverend Frame to Stone. I wept, and told him even from our budding Loves, each circumſtance of what I have now rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, declar'd the Murder, and diſplay'd my Wrongs, begging him to compaſſionate my Cauſe, ſince I was ſtill compel'd to die or love him.</p>
                        <p>Grief ſtop'd his Tongue from making a Reply, but with his Head he bid me quit the Room, to give him liberty to vent his Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. I left him languiſhing to that degree, that Fate ſate daring Reaſon in his Face, which pierc'd my very Soul; as I departed, the look he gave me ſeem'd a laſt Farewel; and 'twas with great compulſion I retir'd, to leave him to the rigid Sourge of Fortune, which, I perceiv'd, did handle him ſeverely.</p>
                        <p>After ſome wretched hours of cloſe retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he forc'd a ſettl'd Mind, and ſent for me; his Countenance appear'd without a Cloud, and every Action had an eaſie Ayr: Smiling, he roſe, and took me by the Hand, and plac'd me on a Seat juſt by him, diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed me with the greateſt Moderation, that I
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:151240:50"/>could hardly credit what I ſaw. Maturely he diſcuſs'd upon each point, and brought it ſubtilely to a kind reſult; told me, that ſince hard Fate had play'd its Game, our Care muſt be to help and crown all future ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagements with good Succeſs; bid me not mourn what I could not redreſs, but learn of him to bear the Laſh of Fortune.</p>
                        <p>I could not judge if this was Artifice, or whether he had overcome his Paſſion, yet parted from him much more ſatisfied, for he had promis'd to reſtore <hi>Octavio,</hi> if I would leave the Conduct to his Will. With hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reſignation I conſented, wholly to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpos'd by his Command; for, I confeſs that my unparallel'd Love fell to the heighth of abject Supplication.</p>
                        <p>Within two days I went from <hi>Madrid,</hi> to paſs the tedious minutes more ſedate, in a ſtill rural Villa of the Viſcount's, that thirty miles ſtood diſtant from the City; there, there how many wretched hours flew, in the reflection of my dubious Deſtiny; no Shade, no Grove, but conſcious of my Grief, my Tears ſupplied each Rivulet and Spring, and every melancholy Grotto ſpoke Deſpair, to the perpetual Volleys of my Sighs.</p>
                        <p>'Twas thus I ſpent the beſt part of a Year, whilſt the kind Viſcount acted things at home beyond the expectation of a Friend, and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly in my behalf he did proceed: he writ
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:151240:50"/>
                           <hi>Octavio</hi> word, That his Fears need not any way oppoſe his coming home, for none could gueſs him guilty of that Crime; beſides, the great Affair which he propos'd could ne'r be decided at that diſtance; therefore 'twas requiſite he ſhould return, to ſettle all in Peace for his advantage: giving ſome hints, that I was then retir'd, leſt that ſhould be a Motive for his ſtaying.</p>
                        <p>It was theſe generous Letters once more induc'd <hi>Octavio</hi> to ſee <hi>Madrid;</hi> the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view between him and the Viſcount, I heard, was very paſſionate and moving, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mitigated in few days, he introduc'd the mournful Tragick Tale, which was the fatal Cauſe of all our Evil: <hi>Octavio</hi> charg'd the weighty Sin on me, whoſe Falſeneſs had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray'd him to that Miſchief, and then the good old Man did weep, to vindicate my much wrong'd Faith and Honour, owning the Act (as really 'twas) his own, to force me on a Match I loath'd and hated. At this <hi>Octavio</hi> ſenſibly was touch'd, and bore a friendly part in my Misfortune, but Love was baniſh'd, all that Stock he ſwore could never be exhauſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, now was ſpent, and I was then reduc'd to ſordid Pity: Nothing could move a kind Conſent to ſee me, his Heart was abſolutely now another's; for tho' upon the Fall of poor <hi>Alcidas</hi> he fled, to ſeek a noble Death, entirely deſpiſing Thoughts of Life, reſiſtleſs
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:151240:51"/>Beauty, that o'erweighs the World, and bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lances bright Virtue with a Bubble, with her engaging Charms ſeiz'd on his wandring Soul, and laid her ſtrict Commands on him to live; he could not view a Miſtreſs ſo abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, nor ſtand the Teſt of my ſevere Reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; nor would he wed the Woman for whoſe ſake his Hands had been imbrew'd in that dear Blood; or rather 'twas his new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born Flame prevail'd, to make him quit the Seat of his Confuſion, and ſeek a Sanctuary of Repoſe on the ſoft Boſom of his choſen Bride.</p>
                        <p>Within ſix Weeks he went from <hi>Madrid,</hi> to proſecute his laſt-eſtabliſh'd Love; nor were there any Offers could reclaim him: Which News the Viſcount would have hid from me, but oh! I had too true Intelligence, Reaſon kept <hi>Argus</hi> Watch, tho' Love was blind; nor could my hundred Eyes be all deluded, too obvious was this laſt ungrateful part for me to be deceiv'd, or Heaven to pardon. I ſcorn'd myſelf, that I could not contemn the Man that had ſo ſlighted and abuſed me; but, oh! impoſſible, I lov'd to that degree, not all my Wrongs had influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to reclaim; ſtill I ador'd, ſtill languiſh'd to retain the moſt perfidious Wretch that ever breath'd; in vain I ſigh'd, in vain de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plor'd the loſs of all my Hopes, the falſe <hi>Octavio,</hi> in whom I yet diſcern'd Ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
<gap reason="missing" extent="4 pages">
                              <desc>〈4 pages missing〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="93" facs="tcp:151240:51"/>Thus you have heard the Fate of poor <hi>Canace,</hi> the moſt unhappy Maid that ever lov'd; hitherto all my Life has been one Plague, and what I am to ſuffer will be great, ſince now the utmoſt proſpect of my Hope is Bankrupt to that laſt and wretched point of learning how to bear with Reſignation.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Don <hi>Lelio,</hi> who had given ſtrict attention to the relation of this mournful Tale, look'd on the lovely Innocent, who wept, and weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pierc'd the Souls of thoſe that heard her, like <hi>April</hi> ſhowrs in Tears ſhe mourn'd, which like the Heavenly Dew drop'd from her Eyes and veil'd the luſtre of thoſe beautious Orbs, and, like an Evening <hi>Zephirus,</hi> her Sighs whiſpering their murmuring Accents through the Air, wrought the Inanimates unto com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion. Thus Sorrow in its Splendor did appear, all moving, all tranſporting, all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging, melting the tender Hearts of the Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctators, who gazing on the melancholy Maid, ſuffer'd the charming Object ſo to pleaſe, they never thought to interrupt her Grief, till they beheld her fall into a Swoon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Melantius,</hi> all o'er Pity and Concern, was ruſhing from his Covert to her ſuccour, when he perceiv'd Don <hi>Lelio</hi> claſp her cloſe, laying her Head upon his panting Boſom, and chaffing gently with his Hands her Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, this application ſummon'd back her life,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:151240:52"/>which by degrees aſſum'd the glorious form, diſperſing through her dying Face a Bloom that warm'd the very Heavens with Deſire, and gave ſuch Satisfaction to Don <hi>Lelio,</hi> that catching her with Rapture in his Arms, he cry'd, <hi>Ceaſe, ceaſe, my deareſt Friend, to be perplex'd,</hi> Octavio <hi>may and ſhall be ſtill thy own, if Time and your Diſeaſe will now permit. Wonders! 'tis Wonders that I have to tell you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At this <hi>Melantius</hi> did again retire, who otherwiſe was going to appear, and make an offering of himſelf to ſerve them. The faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Maid, recover'd by this Speech, rub'd off the Chagreen of all her Woe, and earneſtly compos'd herſelf to hear; the which Don <hi>Lelio</hi> having well obſerv'd, moſt readily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded in this manner:</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="history">
                        <head>The Hiſtory of <hi>Aſpatia.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>LET not an empty Name incurr your Rage, nor be you too too partial in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment, then I'll confeſs myſelf to be <hi>Aſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> that very ſame <hi>Aſpatia</hi> you diſtruſt, yet Honour with ſo high a Character, ſhe whom blind Fortune took delight to jilt, and make the Paſtime of her fickle Humour; ſhe who has met with too ſevere a Curſe; yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious of no weighty Sin but Love, your Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:151240:52"/>once, for evermore your Friend, if you will generouſly embrace the Offer; for know, it was my unexperienc'd years gave me that Title, and not Inclination, Gratitude may ſometimes be miſtook for Paſſion; no more was mine no farther my Concern: But I'll not dare to juſtifie <hi>Octavio;</hi> he who inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly abandons Charms the greateſt Monarch would be proud to boaſt of, can no way make addition to a Crime, of which the World moſt juſtly will accuſe him: Yet ſince 'twas you that firſt engag'd his Heart, and taught it how to love, and to reſent, Pity a Mad-man's Frenzy, 'tis no more, and let me plead for him who is my Ruin.</p>
                        <p>At this ſhe paus'd, and gave <hi>Arioſto</hi> time to view her with Amazement, and Diſorder, Fear, Hope; and Jealouſie at once attack'd, and batter'd her with fierce Artillery; ſhe look'd upon her ſometimes as a Foe, ſometimes a Friend, and knows not which to think her, but prudently her Judgment did ſuſpend, till ſhe had heard the ſequel of the Story.</p>
                        <p>Never till now <hi>Melantius</hi> was ſo loſt, to ſee <hi>Aſpatia</hi> by him in that habit, within the compaſs of his Arms, there in a Country de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate, remote, far from her noble Father and Relations, weeping to craggy Rocks and ſenſleſs Trees, far from that Princely Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor once ſhe us'd to grace the Courts and Palaces of <hi>Lisbon,</hi> where glorious Captives
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:151240:53"/>waited at her Feet, proud to be choſe to do ſome little Service, and where he had ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin'd her in all the Gaiety of Youth and Pleaſure, triumphing o'er a Crowd of bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Hearts, ſtabbing by Frowns, tranſporting by her Smiles, beyond the Wiſhes of fanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Woman: What could this mean? by what ſtrange Miracle found he <hi>Aſpatia,</hi> on the Verge of <hi>Naples?</hi> That ſprightly Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that enſlav'd the World, tracing a ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Grove in Sorrow, waſting the Treaſure of her Youth in Exile; oh! how amazed, how Thunder ſtruck was he, to ſee that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected killing Object, the Miſtreſs of his Soul before his Eyes, with all thoſe Charms that made him firſt her Captive! her whom he unadviſedly abandon'd, whoſe very Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory he once contriv'd to baniſh, too late alas! he found he was deceiv'd, found that the Gods had Intereſt in her Cauſe, and took peculiar care to make it proſper; 'twas hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he gave credit to his Eyes, but really did believe he ſaw a Viſion, wiſhing perpetual Sleep to charm his Senſes, ſtill to retain that dear deluding Phantaſm; but when he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collected from that Thought, and found each Faculty was ſound and perfect, his Wonder and Confuſion did encreaſe, to know what God, what Fate had brought her thither: All angry Reſentments left his Breaſt, inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by Wiſhes and Love's ſofter Fire, the
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:151240:53"/>little God ſate playing in her Eyes and ſhew'd him all the Pleaſure, not the Pain, of dazling Rapture and more fond Deſire, inviting him by all thoſe little Arts that firſt betray'd his eaſie tranquil Mind to the ſubjection of his wanton Snares, to curſe his Rigour, yet adore his Power: Once more he triumphs o'er his bleeding Heart, ſhot thick his Arrows, and ſecur'd his Throne, tickled him with the Feathers of his Dart, till unperceiv'd he fell upon the Steel, and ſmiling at his Wound, ſuck'd in the Poyſon.</p>
                        <p>Don <hi>Lelio</hi>'s Dreſs did render him more fair, expoſing Beauties that were made to conquer; Charms that had been conceal'd lay open now, Limbs the moſt regular and moſt ſurprizing. Loſt in a mighty Extaſie, he gaz'd, dying and languiſhing for the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion; not one paſt Injury did grate his Soul, or diſcompoſe its raviſh'd Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; Reſentment fled beyond the very Clouds, and buried all his Wrongs in dark Oblivion. The Nymph, all chaſt and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, did look youthful, engaging, beautiful and tempting, and to his Eyes appear'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a blemiſh: None but his wretched ſelf he did accuſe and tax with too much Folly and Credulity, who raſhly had forſook, for the firſt Fault, the moſt deſerving Creature in the World: If ſhe had Sence, he knew ſhe muſt reſent it, and therefore was diſtracted
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:151240:54"/>with his Fears, how to retrieve the Intereſt he had loſt: With Looks unguarded, and unbounded Thoughts, he gave away the rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of his Soul, each wandring Faculty, caught by ſurprize, was made a ſecond and ſubſtantial Conqueſt, prompt by Diſtruſt and violent Deſire, his breaking Heart no longer could reſiſt, but was juſt falling at her Feet for Mercy, when the diſtreſſed fair One thus broke ſilence, and Curioſity ſtop'd his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding:</p>
                        <p>That I am Daughter to the Duke <hi>Antonio de Almeyda,</hi> I bluſh to own, having the leaſt deſerv'd that worthy Lot, and moſt abuſed my Intereſt in that Name: My Mother, who deriv'd from no inconſiderable Branch of the <hi>Piacenze</hi>'s Dukes, had all Advantages that could compleat a Beauty; for, beſides the rare Perfections of her Perſon, ſhe had Wit, Fortitude, Judgment, and Virtue, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got her the Applauſe, Admiration, and Eſteem of all that knew her: ſhe was univerſally a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor'd, and induſtriouſly ſought for by all the neighbouring Princes in <hi>Italy;</hi> nor did a Stranger paſs throughout the Country, that made it not his chiefeſt care to ſee the fine <hi>Charlott,</hi> ſo was ſhe call'd.</p>
                        <p>Amongſt the reſt, it was the Duke <hi>d' Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meyda</hi>'s chance (who was juſt then come to that Title by the Death of his Father) to travel through <hi>Parma,</hi> where ſhe then reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded;
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:151240:54"/>he reſolv'd not to quit the City till he had a ſight of this lovely celebrated Beauty, which was no hard matter for a Man of his Quality. He ſaw, and was convinc'd, gave up his Freedom at the fatal View, and ever after own'd himſelf her <hi>Slave.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Their Amour was romantick and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining, but too tedious to recite here, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore paſſing over all Preliminaries, we arrive at their Nuptials, which was very noble and magnificent, with ſplendid Maſques, Balls and Tournaments, wherein all the youthful Nobility aſſembl'd, and perform'd diverſity of Gallantries: Three years after Marriage the Duke ſtay'd in that Country, by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion of his Wife, who found no ſmall. Regret to leave her Native Soil; but at length, urg'd by neceſſity of ſome weighty Affairs, wherein the Duke had been a very conſiderable Loſer, they were forc'd on their Journey at a very inconvenient time for my Mother, who was then eight months gone with Child of me, Heaven had already bleſs'd them with a <hi>Son,</hi> whoſe graceful Aſpect pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd early <hi>Virtues:</hi> Not much above one year they had enjoy'd him, when they ſet forward towards <hi>Portugal;</hi> they met with a pleaſant Land-Journey, and embarqued with as fair a Proſpect, but that over-ruling Power that finds it expedient ſometimes to daſh our ſweeteſt Cups with Gall, preſented them a
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:151240:55"/>too too bitter Draught, which when com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel'd by Fate, there's no Man can reſiſt.</p>
                        <p>They were within ſome few hours ſail of ſhore, when the Heavens overcaſt, and a dreadful Storm aroſe, which prov'd only a direful Omen of their Misfortunes, for in leſs than half an hour it clear'd again to pleaſant calmneſs and ſerenity; when from the Top<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſt-head they 'ſpied a <hi>Ship</hi> that gave them chace, with all the ſail that ſhe could make they crowded down upon them; they were in ſome conſternation and ſurprize, but the Duke, whoſe noble <hi>Soul</hi> could ne'r admit of Fear, took all the moſt convenient methods for defence that the ſhort time would give him leave. Now, by the nigh approach, to their Perplexity, they diſcern'd her to be a famous Pyrate, who for many years had ſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thoſe <hi>Seas;</hi> no way they had to eſcape, for their Adverſary having the Wind, ſoon boarded them. The Duke at this time per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd Wonders, but having few Aſſiſtants beſides his own Attendants, and not being well provided for what ſo little was expected, after a ſtout defence, which ſtartled much the Pyrates, by deſperate Multitudes he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puls'd: They being now the Maſters of the <hi>Ship,</hi> grew inſolent, and rifled all their Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, clapping the <hi>Sailors</hi> under Hatches, and making all their Prize. My Mother, who had endur'd all the violence of Fears and
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:151240:55"/>Terrour, at this laſt Scene of immediate Death or Slavery, fell with the direful Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination into a Swoon. The Duke being luc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kily by, receiv'd her in his Arms, and altho' his Reflections did preſent him with too clear a Proſpect of their Woe, he us'd all the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence and tender Applications that could recover her, and encourage her to bear Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e with a Patience worthy of herſelf. It was a conſiderable time before he was convinc'd ſhe liv'd, and the fatal demonſtration ſerv'd but to involve him in a greater Doubt; for the warm Perſwaſions he had whiſper'd, ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned back ſome fleeting Hopes, and untimely diſclos'd her Eyes, to be a Spectator of young <hi>Frederick</hi> (their only Child) and his Nurſe, juſt forc'd on board the Pyrate. This Sight renews her former Grief, and ſunk her with the weight of Deſperation: Nor was the Duke, with all his Fortitude, now in conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to addreſs a Comfort, he ſaw his Wife expiring at his Feet, his Child a Captive to inſulting Villains, and he the ſinking Prop that ſhould relieve them; Love, Pity, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity divides his Breaſt, and equally demands his kind Aſſiſtance, but all the Means was taken from his Hands, and he had nothing left but his bare Wiſhes, which was reduc'd to wiſh himſelf, and his dear Wife, next Prey, that they might ſuffer all together.</p>
                        <p>Whilſt he ſtood in this Extremity of
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:151240:56"/>Care, a violent and unexpected Hurricane a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe, and ſeparated the Ships, which lay gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled together, the fury of the Tempeſt drove them ſo faſt, that in ſhort time they loſt ſight of each other: The Seamen, who were very induſtrious at their Plunder, were moſt of them in the Long-boat, conveying off their Booty, and but two at this time left on board the Duke, abject Raſcals, who finding their Neceſſity, meanly were imploring for their Lives, but the Duke, who was wholly taken up with his <hi>Sorrow,</hi> had but juſt reaſon enough left to releaſe his own <hi>Seamen,</hi> to whoſe Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy he left them, and from whoſe hand they receiv'd their Deaths, whilſt he imploy'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the recovery of my Mother: Grief, and the cruel Sufferings ſhe underwent had taken full poſſeſſion of her Heart, and it was with great difficulty they kept her <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Body</hi> together, till they made a Port in <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garves,</hi> call'd <hi>Tavila,</hi> where ſhe had not been two days, but ſhe was deliver'd of me, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time before the uſual ſeaſon, and deliver'd up her Life at the ſame minute: My Father was the moſt afflicted Man in the World, and had it not been in conſideration of me, which oblig'd him to preſerve his Life, in care to mine, he hardly had ſurviv'd my Mother. He ſtay'd not long after the Funeral-Rites, but took me, with my Nurſe, to a Houſe he has near <hi>Ville-Neuove,</hi> where he liv'd a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>engag'd
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:151240:56"/>and retired Life, till I attained the Years of Fourteen, at which time he thought it convenient to introduce me into the World, that I might be the better capable of acting for my ſelf: We then remov'd to <hi>Lisbon,</hi> where we liv'd with all the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur that could render an advantage to my blooming Years, I had the Priviledge of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiting the Court, and ſome publick Places, which, in a ſhort time, got me not a few Admirers. The Duke was willing to ſee me well diſpoſed of, and incouraged thoſe of the moſt Illuſtrious Families, and of the greateſt Characters, for me to make my Choice; but I being only taken with the Gallantry and Addreſs, liv'd with a cold Indifference to the Sex, and could not be prevail'd upon to Marry.</p>
                        <p>It was at this time, that my ſmall Beauty gained ſome little Fame at <hi>Lisbon,</hi> when <hi>Octavio</hi> appear'd at Court, and was gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally reported, a Noble Cavalier, but one whoſe nice Virtues were eclipſed by a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Melancholly, there lack'd not thoſe who imputed it to Love, and apply'd it to ſeveral of our Beauties, yet knew no more then from their bare Opinion; he had the good luck to be particularly receiv'd amongſt the Ladies; and I confeſs my ſelf, that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten I have view'd him with ſome Pleaſure: He had ſomething in his Aſpect that attract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:151240:57"/>all Eyes, and ſomething in his Diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo engaging, that there was no beholding him with bare Indifference; yet mine was Admiration, and not Love, which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards I was too dear convinc'd of: Several ſmall Services I had receiv'd, which paſt with me but as his common Humour, till a more evident Addreſs too fatally inform'd me; Madrigals, Songs, and <hi>Billet-doux,</hi> he ſent; by Night with Sighs and Serenades he entertain'd me; by theſe and a thouſand o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ways, he oft declared the Meſſage of his Heart, which found more free acceſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my Breaſt, then all the Gallantry I knew before; yet I had Conduct to conceal my Thoughts, and gave him not the leaſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, but rather ſeem'd vext at his ill plac'd Paſſion; ſome Months paſs'd on with this Amuſement, without much Love, or much Conſideration, till daily Services inhaunced the Store of mighty Favours, that I began to fear the Payment; hitherto he had no acceſs into our Houſe, and found it difficult to gain my Preſence, till a moſt fam'd remarkable Exploit, gave him a fair, and plauſible Pretenſion:</p>
                        <p>One Day at a famous Match of Hunting, where moſt of the Nobility (then reſiding at <hi>Lisbon</hi>) participated of the Diverſion, Ladies as well as Men, were in the Field to ſee the Paſtime, and partake of the Chace, I
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:151240:57"/>being mounted on a fierce <hi>Arrabian</hi> Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, followed the Game with earneſt ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; my Inclination to thoſe Country Sports, and the Rural Life I had been uſed to, gave me opportunity to make my ſelf a compleat Horſe-woman: I was now hot in purſuance of the Chace, and gave full Reins to my Horſe, without conſideration, when a Servant followed me to deliver a Tablet I had dropt, which I turning back to receive, juſt as I was at the brink of a rapid River, and not checking my ſpeed, the Horſe not being uſed to boggle at any oppoſition, took the Water, and before I could recover, plung'd into the Stream, where with the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence of the Flood, and ſtrugling of the Beaſt, I loſt my Saddle, and was left float<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
                        <p>All that ſaw this Accident, were in great Conſternation how to deliver me from the danger, yet was cautious of themſelves, but the Duke my Father, urg'd by his Paternal Love and Care, deſperately purſued me in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the River, where inſtead of preſerving me, he met with the ſame Misfortune, and we had like to have ſunk together, had not the Brave <hi>Octavio,</hi> (who was then on the top of a Bridge built over the Stream) ſeeing our Diſtreſs, quited his Horſe, and like <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> or ſome Guardian Deity leapt in to ſave us: The Event anſwered his Deſign, for
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:151240:58"/>after ſome little ſtrugling, he recovered us both, and ſwam with us out in each Hand in Triumph.</p>
                        <p>This God-like Action begot Admiration in all the Spectators, but for our parts, that had not yet ſence to know our Safety, or Deliverer, ſtupid, and half dead, we were conveyed to a Grange within view, where the beſt means was uſed to recover us: And here <hi>Octavio</hi>'s Gallantry was more obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, in refuſing to ſhift his Cloaths till he was confirm'd we lived.</p>
                        <p>From theſe generous Actions, (after the Recovery of a dangerous Sickneſs it gave us both) <hi>Octavio</hi> became the Darling Friend of the Duke, and their Intimacy grew ſo remarkable, that it was a great Chance to find them ſeparate; a long while <hi>Octavio</hi> was ſo brave to ſtifle all his Hopes, with feigned Indifference, being loath to urge the mighty Obligation, till Love, reſiſtleſs Love overcame his Will, and added greater hopes to gratifie his Paſſion, no longer could he bare the hard Reſtraint, but willing to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove his fleeting Hours, began a more ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Court then ever yet he had pretended to. From my Youth, and Unexperience, and the particular Eſteem I had ever found for <hi>Octavio,</hi> I was inclinable to believe I Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, he being the firſt Man that could ever warm me into a Liking, and conſidering the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:151240:58"/>Duke was juſt upon the Deſign of Marrying me, Gratitude, and ſome ſmall Inclination, made me not violent to oppoſe a Flame, I thought I could better diſpence with than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; but the Duke, ſince the Misfortune of his Wife and Son, having fixt his future Bliſs, and utmoſt Hopes in me, and lived Unmarried to make me Great and Fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, could not bare the Thoughts of my Separation to another Kingdom; and I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally believe there was nothing but <hi>Octavio</hi>'s being a Stranger, diſappointed his Wiſhes; he declined it with all the Compliſance in the World, conferring daily Favours on him, and generous Offers to compenſate, if poſſible, for the Lives he had received at his Hands, without ſo dear an Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not forgetting prviate Commands to me, not to allow or encourage his Addreſs: but I, from the Duke's Affection to him, not expecting this Repulſe, had raſhly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced too far, and tho' it was not difficult for my Heart to recant, yet Duty oblig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me to refer my ſelf to my Father, and Honour to excuſe my ſelf under the ſame pretext to him.</p>
                        <p>Affairs were in this manner between us, when <hi>Octavio</hi> was ſummoned Home to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drid,</hi> which he evaded a long time, nor would not depart till I had promiſed him, if he could gain the Duke's Conſent, he ſhould
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:151240:59"/>not fail of mine; we had private Enterviews by the Aſſiſtance of my Maid, where through his Interceſſion, I aſſented to a Correſpondence during his Abſence, for the grateful Sentiments I had entertained of him fince his reſcuing us from Death, made it dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicult for me to deny him any reaſonable Requeſt.</p>
                        <p>With theſe Aſſurances, tho' not without great Regret, he ſet forward his Journey; I was not under the eaſieſt Circumſtances when we parted, but Time, and a more dear, yet cruel Remedy, ſoon diſingag'd thoſe Cares.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Melantius,</hi> Son to the Marqueſs <hi>de Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganes,</hi> juſt return'd from his Studies, (a young Cavalier, Charming as a God, Beautiful to a Wonder, Wiſe as <hi>Apollo;</hi> Juſt, Heroick, Affable and Courteous, Gallant and Enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging; a Face, a Shape, and Wit form'd for Love and Succeſs:) (Heavens! I Rave) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came my Lover. Then, and not till then, my panting Heart, learnt to diſtinguiſh a real Paſſion, from that of an imaginary En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement. Gods! With what new Fire was my Breaſt enflam'd, and how exquiſite was the dear ſence of all my Joys and Doubts; and how different from the feeble warmth I felt before? But to Behold him was too great a Bliſs: To hear him Speak, or Touch him, was a Heaven of boundleſs
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:151240:59"/>Pleaſures, and thrilling Satisfaction, and to imagine more, was not to live.</p>
                        <p>Scarce had ſhe ended this laſt Accent with a Sigh, but <hi>Melantius</hi> (charm'd to an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expreſſible degree, flung himſelf at her Feet, (forgeting all paſt Jealouſies and Fears) throughly convinc'd of his Miſtake, with eager Kiſſes he devour'd her Hand, ſigh'd on her Knees, and panting on her Breaſt, aſſoon as e'er his Paſſion would give leave, with a tranſported Joy, he burſt into theſe words: <hi>Be falſe! Be vain! if poſſible you can; ſtill, ſtill I am born to Love and to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore you.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Aſpatia</hi> thus luckily and ſtrangely ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, could hardly give a credit to her Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and it appear'd incredible to all, a too ſubſtantial Bleſſing to be real, Dumb with Amazement, ſilently they gazed, and gave themſelves intirely up to Wonder: But <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatia,</hi> whoſe more particular Intereſt had involved her in a thouſand doubtful Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions, had much ado to recover from the Agitation, either exceſs of Joy or Fear had drove her to. As ſoon as ſhe was convinc'd by the tender Imbraces of her Lover, that it was no Illuſion, ſhe fain would have aſſum'd a Neglect and Reſentment equivolent to the Injuries ſhe had receiv'd, but Inclination, and Reflection that he had took her at too
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:151240:60"/>critical an advantage to impoſe an Affectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhe diſpens'd with Form, and raiſing him from the Ground, with Eyes all Love and languiſhing, ſhe ſaid, <hi>Riſe to my Arms, thou dear, thou cruel Man, and once again receive thy own</hi> Aſpatia. <hi>Melantius</hi> ſprung at the Invitation to the Boſom of the Fair, which was panting him a Welcome, where in equal Raptures, they were a long time Claſp'd, till <hi>Aſpatia</hi>'s Curioſity (to know by what prodigious Chance, they had ſo wonderfully met) rous'd her. <hi>Melantius,</hi> after a Complement to <hi>Don Arioſto</hi> (whom he ſaluted by the Name of <hi>Canace,</hi> giving her to underſtand he had overheard her Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and wiſhing her as quick a turn of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune) and ſome kind notice of <hi>Carlo</hi> (whom he diſcovered was the truſty <hi>Laura</hi>) gave them a punctual and diverting Narrative of his Life, from his quitting <hi>Portugal,</hi> to that happy Minute.</p>
                        <p>By this time a Reconciliation and Intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy was ſeal'd on all hands, and their Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machs giving them a Summons, they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journ'd to the Cabbin, referring the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of <hi>Aſpatia</hi>'s Story to the Afternoon; which when ſhe had finiſh'd, and <hi>Melantius</hi> was confirm'd his Miſtreſs had been Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, tranſported at the News, he preſt returning Home, that they at once might ſatisfie their Parents, and compleat their
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:151240:60"/>own Felicity: <hi>Aſpatia,</hi> weary of that way of living, required no perſwaſions to a thing ſhe already was impatient to put in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Don Arioſto,</hi> who had determined never to leave <hi>Aſpatia,</hi> was doubly now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to accompany them to a place, where probably ſhe might retrieve her Lover<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>; only deſiring the Liberty to continue the Habit ſhe was then in, till ſome fair occaſion preſented for her to change it.</p>
                        <p>Thus being agreed, <hi>Melantius</hi> took leave for that Night, that he might diſcharge himſelf from his Command in the Army, and early the next Morning return'd with <hi>Montal,</hi> whom he order'd with Speed to provide for their Departure; where we will leave them on that Deſign, and return to <hi>Octavio,</hi> whom we left almoſt Expiring.</p>
                        <p>Grief, Diſappointments, and the Anguiſh of <hi>Octavio</hi>'s Wound, had reduc'd him to a violent Feavor, which daily increaſing to the hazard of his Life, it was thought ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient, to ſend for a Prieſt to perform the laſt good Office: <hi>Adrian</hi> a <hi>Franciſcan</hi> Fryar in the Neighbourhood, a pious and judicious Man, heard his Confeſſion; after which Introduction, he became a conſtant Viſiter; ſomething in <hi>Octavio</hi>'s Perſon won his Soul, and he reſolved with care and diligence to ſerve him; his Diſtreſs and ill Accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion mov'd him with Compaſſion. This
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:151240:61"/>Kindneſs was obſerv'd by poor <hi>Octavio,</hi> who as far as his Ability, made a grateful Return. The good Humour and Sanctity of Father <hi>Adrian,</hi> had begot ſo great an Eſteem in <hi>Octavio,</hi> that at Intervals he made him his Confident; and now finding himſelf grow worſe, he truſted him to acquaint the Viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count <hi>Bozzolos,</hi> where, and under what Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance he was, which a long time he had been a Stranger to. Upon the firſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice the good old Viſcount, fearing the Deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of his Family, and inevitable Ruine of all his Joys, made no ſtay for reply, but without conſideration of the Fatigue, got all things ready, and the next Day ſet Sail for <hi>Portugal;</hi> the Ship put into the Port of <hi>Velle-Neue</hi> for Water, and the Viſcount impatient to ſee <hi>Octavio,</hi> tho 'twas with more trouble to a Man of his Age, yet for more diſpatch, reſolved to perform the reft of his Journey on that leſs dangerous Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: He took but the reſpite of the Night, and the next Morning mounted Horſe for <hi>Porto,</hi> with Alacrity and Speed, he ſet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, being attended for twelve Miles to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with a cool Breeze that render'd the bluſhing Cheeks of <hi>Aurora</hi> very refreſhing: About this time he arrived in a pleaſant Vale, (where the Duke <hi>de Almeyda,</hi> and the Marqueſs <hi>de Leganes</hi> were a Hunting) the Viſcount's Horſe ſtarting at the approach
<gap reason="missing" extent="4 pages">
                              <desc>〈4 pages missing〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb n="117" facs="tcp:151240:61"/>Peace, and took care, as much as poſſible, to conceal my concern from her; but when I found my ſelf oppreſt, took Horſe, and under pretence of taking the Air, privately indulg'd my Sorrow.</p>
                        <p>In one of theſe melancholly Humours, as I was moving along the Shore, by the vaſt Billows that came rolling in upon me, and the mountainous height of the ſwelling Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; I rais'd my Eyes that were fixt on the Ground, to contemplate that Emblem of the impetuous Storm in my Breaſt, when I perceived a Veſſel ſtrugling with the Wind, endeavouring with all her Skill to plow her Paſſage to the Iſland of <hi>Sicily,</hi> whilſt the ſwelling Seas repuls'd her Courſe, and the rapid Waves forc'd her back as faſt: This Conteſt of the angry Floods, and the Sai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers Task to oppoſe 'em, took up my Thoughts, till I ſaw the raging Tempeſt ruſh the ſhattered Veſſel on the Sands be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me, where Waves after Waves daſht on her Sides with their reſiſtleſs force, ſtart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Planks, and leaving Breaches that unſatiably receiv'd the Torrents that pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in, till Drunk with the Deluge, ſhe tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled down, and ſunk with her Freight and moſt of her Men; Deſpair or Hopes made ſome attempt to ſtem the Tempeſt, others to catch at Planks, but all in vain, none could float to Shoar, but unable to ſuſtain the Conquering Main, ſunk in the Gulph to
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:151240:62"/>the <hi>Stygian</hi> Lake; except a few, whoſe luckier Thoughts had prompted them to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the Long-Boat, and with great diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty ſaved their Lives.</p>
                        <p>I made up to the place where they Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, being curious to know their Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and found they were all Sailers; but one who was their Captain, and a Boy about a Year old, very Beautiful and richly Clad; I was ſtrangely taken with the Child, who infinitely reſembled mine, and enquir'd his Birth and Country; but they very rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily told me, That therein they could not ſatisfie me, for they knew not themſelves, confeſſing they were Pirats, and that in their Courſe towards <hi>Portugal,</hi> had met with a conſiderable Prize, and again loſt it in the late Wrack; their Child they imagined to be by its Splendour a Nobleman's aboard the Ship they Plunder'd, but whoſe they could not tell; for being ſuddenly ſeparated by a furious Storm, they had not time to ſecure more than the Child and his Nurſe, who either for fear or ſpite dyed in half an hour after ſhe was taken; the Child was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in hopes of Ranſom, or rather Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence deſign'd him for a better Fate.</p>
                        <p>The Duke <hi>de Almeyda,</hi> who had attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with violent Emotions this part of the Story, was no longer able to forbear inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting him, but with an inſupportable A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gony, and the moſt violent Concern in the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:151240:62"/>World, he enquired what Fortune ſince had attended that inſtant: The Viſcount won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering at his Diſturbance, only made anſwer, <hi>I hope he Lives;</hi> and began to examine, if he had any Intereſt in ſuch a Loſs? The Duke in Tears briefly related his Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes; his Ship-wrack, the Death of his Wife, and loſs of his Child; which being ended, he preſt with all violence to know if he had no Mark, no Remnant of his Cloaths, by which he might be convinc'd of his Hopes.</p>
                        <p>The Viſcount having earneſtly heard him, reply'd, How glad am I, and how ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily ſhall I depart this Life, ſince I leave my <hi>Octavio</hi> ſo brave, ſo good a Father, for I am more than perſwaded he is your real Son, look on this Signet; took from off his Neck, wherein a handſome Cypher is ingraved, and call it to remembrance if you can.</p>
                        <p>No ſooner had the Duke ſurvey'd it, but with all the Joy imaginable he cry'd out, Thou infallible Oracle of Truth, I am now confirm'd from theſe dear Characters which contain the Names of my ſelf and Wife, that it is the ſame young <hi>Frederick</hi> wore, when he was Raviſh'd from us; and thou my <hi>Guardian Angel,</hi> let me know, by what ſtrange Providence you have preſerv'd the firſt dear Pledge of all my ſacred Vows, that in my trembling Arms I may receive the happy Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of my future Peace, and pant upon thy Breaſt ten thouſand Bleſſings, before my joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Soul expire with Tranſport.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="120" facs="tcp:151240:63"/>The Viſcount much ſurpriz'd at this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, and much pleas'd to find he had fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtered ſuch a Noble Off-ſpring, proceeded to his Relation.</p>
                        <p>Sir, (ſaid he) this Child I Ranſom'd from the Pirats, with no inconſiderable Sum of Gold, and with an unuſual ſatisfaction bore him Home with me, where having told the whole Adventure, it was look'd upon as a particular Regard Heaven had of my Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and therefore had thus miraculouſly ſent this Child to propagate my Name and Family, in lieu of that I had loſt; my Wife being from ſome Reaſons ſo poſſeſs'd by the Phyſicians, to be paſt hopes of more, it ſeem'd plauſible to me, and from a wonderful Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction I had took to the Child, I was incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to believe it the Decree of Heaven, and immediately with the Conſent of my Wife, Adopts him; and from his ſtrange re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance of my own, nam'd him after the Deceas'd <hi>Octavio:</hi> This was manag'd with all prudent Care and Privacy, and had the good luck never to be ſuſpected, which was a great Satisfaction to all but my Wife, whom it had a quite different Effect on, for the mighty Pleaſure ſhe ſaw us take in the early Virtues of that Infant, rack'd her with Imaginations of the double Joys ſhe had received from her own; which her Humble, Modeſt Diſpoſition endeavouring to conceal from me, for want of Redreſs in time, broke her Heart.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="121" facs="tcp:151240:63"/>From hence the Viſcount miſs'd not a tittle of <hi>Octavio</hi>'s Life, to that of Fryar <hi>Adrian</hi>'s ſending for him to a place near <hi>Porto,</hi> where <hi>Melantius</hi> left him wounded: <hi>I was haſting thither</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>when I met with this ill ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident, which now I bear with leſs regret, ſince it has procured me your acquaintance, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd ſo happy a Secret:</hi> concluding it was alwaies his Deſign before he died, to tell <hi>Octavio</hi> of his obſcure Birth, that he might eſteem himſelf doubly engag'd to the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of the <hi>Bozzo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>o</hi>'s, (that had choſe him when Fate had reduc'd him to the ſtation of a <hi>Plebean</hi>) as likewiſe to put him upon ſome glorious Attempt, to demonſtrate to the World, that his Birth was noble, which he ever believ'd, tho' till that lucky minute could never be convinc'd of: <hi>Notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>I have made it my ſearch this five and twenty years, I wonder'd much I ne'r could find it out; for beſides the token of this Cypher, and his ſwadling Clothes, he has that infallible Mark.</hi> In haſte the Duke did inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt him there, <hi>A Star my</hi> Frederick <hi>bears upon his Breaſt. The ſame has my</hi> Octavio, cry'd the Viſcount. Not till this period did the Duke recollect how much this long Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe might diſcompoſe the Viſcount, and being throughly convinc'd, and overjoy'd at this Diſcovery; careſſing him with all the Gratitude imaginable he left him to Repoſe.</p>
                        <p>Immediately he order'd his Coach to fetch
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:151240:64"/>
                           <hi>Octavio,</hi> waiting with violent impatience his arrival. By this time <hi>Octavio</hi> was pretty well recover'd, and not hearing from the Viſcount, was preparing with all expedition for <hi>Italy,</hi> when the Duke's Orders arrived: He knew not what to think of the Invitation, but knowing the Duke to be in all reſpects the moſt nice in Honour, he could not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend a Trick; beſides, the Equipage and Addreſs had too good a face of Friendſhip to be cover'd with Deceit; he ſcorns to diſtruſt, and reſolves to comply, and in order to that acquaints his Friend <hi>Adrian</hi> with this Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, deſiring he would accompany him; <hi>Adrian</hi> readily conſented, and they ſet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward on their Journey. They were no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner arriv'd, but the Duke met <hi>Octavio</hi> with Tears of Joy, telling him, That Providence had put it in his power to compenſate a little for the Favours he had receiv'd from him, for Heaven, in ſome ſmall Capacity had made him the happy Inſtrument of ſerving his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who in his ſpeed to viſit him had broke his Leg, and now lay dangerouſly ill in his Houſe, at whoſe requeſt he had ſent for him, (he fear'd) to take his laſt Farewel.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Octavio</hi> return'd the Duke the heartieſt Thanks Gratitude could frame; and having curs'd his Stars and Deſtiny, for drawing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch Troubles all that he lov'd or valued, he beg'd to be conducted to his Father; the Duke himſelf was his Guide, who drew open
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:151240:64"/>the Curtains, and preſented him to the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcount. <hi>Octavio</hi> ſoon recall'd him to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, tho' his Sickneſs had much transfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med him, and falling on his Knees, implor'd his Bleſſing, and then religiouſly beg'd Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for his Recovery. He deſir'd him to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute the Misfortunes he had brought to his Relations and Friends, as the heavieſt Plague on his own Head, it being the Decree of Heaven, and not within his power to avert.</p>
                        <p>The Viſcount embraced him with all ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, and after a pious Benediction, told him, 'twas eaſie to forgive him any thing, ſo great was his Paternal Care and Love; his joy was mighty for his Welfare, which he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated by no common ſatisfaction.</p>
                        <p>But now (ſaid he) prepare, my dear <hi>Octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vio,</hi> to hear a moſt ſurprizing, unexpected Story; you are no more my Son; turn to the Duke, and pay that due Obedience, to that moſt glorious Author of your being; but when I am dead and gone, (as ſoon I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ear I ſhall) with grateful thoughts remember how I lov'd you. This Speech confounded ſo <hi>Octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vio,</hi> that he began to think his Brain diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per'd; but the Duke not having patience to wait longer, fell on his Neck, and told him it was true: he ſent immediately for the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs <hi>de Leganes,</hi> and Father <hi>Adrian,</hi> to whom at large he did relate each circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance the <hi>Viſcount</hi> had told him, as well as that of his own Knowledge; which agreeing
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:151240:65"/>ſo exactly, even to the Mark on his left ſide, it ſoon put the reality beyond diſpute. This when <hi>Octavio</hi> heard, and was ſo well convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of, with all ſubmiſſion he addreſſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to his new Father, who received him in his Arms with exquiſite delight, pouring forth Bleſſings on him, and confirming him his by the Name of <hi>Frederick,</hi> which Name for the future he order'd him to aſſume. <hi>Frederick,</hi> after this, applied himſelf to the <hi>Viſcount,</hi> profeſſing all Acknowledgments a generous Soul could ſhew for ſuch unparallel'd Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours: He told him he would ſtill eſteem him as a Parent, ſerve and obey him with the Duty of a Son, and to the World declare his noble Uſage.</p>
                        <p>This News was ſoon diſpers'd thro' <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugal,</hi> and every one congratulated the Duke's good Fortune: But poor <hi>Frederick</hi>'s Soul was ſo oppreſs'd with Sorrow, that all the Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction he receiv'd ſtom this Diſcovery, was, that ſince his Birth had doubtful been, he prov'd a Branch of ſuch a noble Stock, and luckily was hinder'd from adding to his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Sins, by marrying of his Siſter: But the Blood of <hi>Alcidas</hi> lay ſo heavy on his Breaſt, he ne'r had Hopes of any real Comfort, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was under much concern, that theſe Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs had prevented his deſign of leading a Monaſtick Life, which his own Deſire and Fryar <hi>Adrian</hi>'s Advice did prompt him to, by way of Expiation for the Murder of his
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:151240:65"/>Friend. 'Twas with theſe Hopes he kept the Fryar with him, flattering himſelf, that one day he ſhould have an Opportunity to put in execution what he ſo much deſir'd.</p>
                        <p>This he reſolved, but otherwiſe Fate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed; for in an Evening, to compleat their Joy, (ſome three months after this Diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which minutes he melancholy had paſs'd) enter'd the Room (where they were all aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled) <hi>Melant us, Aſpatia, Canace,</hi> (in her Cavaliers Dreſs) <hi>Laura</hi> and <hi>Montal;</hi> which unexpected Gueſts amazed them all: Their Wonder was ſo great, that for ſome time they gaz'd confuſedly upon each other, without the power of moving or of ſpeaking. <hi>Aſpatia</hi> firſt broke ſilence, who proſtrate at her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Feet, with all the Rhetorick that ſhe could uſe, deſir'd his Pardon: The good In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent Duke o'erflow'd with joy to ſee his Daughter: her Pardon eaſily upon her Lips he ſeal'd, and raiſing her from off the ground, cried, <hi>Welcome my dear</hi> Aſpatia. With no leſs joy the Marqueſs <hi>de Leganes</hi> ſaw and receiv'd <hi>Melantius,</hi> and declar'd Heaven ſhow'd ſo ſtrong a hand in all theſe Revolutions, that they were both convinc'd 'twas ſo decreed by Providence, to make the Event ſucceſsful to them all. During this time <hi>Canace</hi> was all Anxiety, ſtriving to bear an equal part be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her Lover, whoſe Eyes ſhe found more lovely now than ever.</p>
                        <p>From their firſt entrance her Eyes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>re
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:151240:66"/>fixt upon him, and hardly could ſhe ſtop the violent ſallies of her Jealouſie, altho' ſhe knew <hi>Aſpatia</hi> was his Siſter, which they had been inform'd of on their Journey, the Fame of ſo remarkable a thing having rung throughout the Kingdom.</p>
                        <p>Curious was the Interview between <hi>Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick</hi> and his Siſter; his Paſſion now was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly turn'd to Friendſhip, and he could gaze upon her without love; he confeſs'd the Pain and miſery that all-along had waited on that Flame, had ſufficiently reveng'd his Baſeneſs to <hi>Canace,</hi> whom he ſtill own'd the Miſtreſs of his Soul; but Revenge, a raſh Vow, and the Contempt ſhe had baffled him with (as he imagin'd) made him ſo violent in his laſt Amour; but now he finds 'twas manag'd by an unſeen Power, who by hidden ways, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond our comprehenſion, eaſily brings the darkeſt things to light. <hi>That power</hi> (replied <hi>Aſpatia</hi>) <hi>we are all oblig'd to, who by this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery had prevented wondrous Miſchief, that muſt have enſued; and now there remains no more to compleat an univerſal Happineſs but the fair, the conſtant, the virtuous</hi> Canace. At this Don <hi>Frederick</hi> bluſh'd, and ſighing ſaid, <hi>Tho' I can love ſincerely none but her, yet by a direful Imprecation I have raſhly made, Gods, that I live to ſpeak it! ſhe never can be mine. Canace,</hi> who had heard with pleaſure the moſt part of this <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> felt ſo violent an effect of Paſſion at this Part, that, unable to
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:151240:66"/>repel its force, ſhe fell into a Swoon. All run to the aſſiſtance of the young Cavalier, and wonder'd at the occaſion of his ſudden Illneſs. <hi>Aſpatia</hi> thinking it a fair opportunity to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover her, readily reveals both Perſon and Diſeaſe; he was ſenſibly concern'd, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany joyning in her behalf, repreſenting her matchleſs Love and Conſtancy, he took her in his Arms, (who was but juſt reviv'd) and preſſing her upon his panting Breaſt, with a Sigh that almoſt burſt his Heart, he cry'd, <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs 'tis poſſible to call my Friend</hi> Alcidas <hi>from the Grave, I cannot wed</hi> Canace.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Adrain,</hi> who till now had been a bare Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctator, thought it high time to act his part; and in order to it, having demanded an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, pull'd off a Beard and falſe Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brows, which hitherto he had wore for a Diſguiſe; and with a Smile took <hi>Frederick</hi> by one Hand, and <hi>Canace</hi> by the other, told them, That Heaven, in regard of their mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Affection, had rais'd <hi>Acidas</hi> from the Dead to do that Friendly Office for them. All that knew him formerly were convine'd 'twas the ſame, and was more aſtoniſhed at this Adventure, then all that had happened to them before; but <hi>Frederick</hi> ſtill doubtful of his good Fortune, had ſcarce Faith to credit what he ſaw, not daring to give way to any Joy, leaſt he ſhould meet a Diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment. <hi>Alcidas</hi> obſerving this, ran to embrace him, and with a Voice that ſhow'd
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:151240:67"/>his mighty Joy, (he cry'd) <hi>Doubt not, my der</hi> Octavio, <hi>for now you hold with is your Arms your Real former Friend</hi> Alcidas, <hi>who now is throughly ſatisfy'd of the Contrition, for that unhappy Deed which Love, Deſpair, and Jealouſie provokt you to; and ſince I have been the fatal Cauſe of your Misfortunes, I think it now my part to ask a Pardon.</hi> At this <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick</hi> being convinc'd, tho' with no ſmall wonder receiv'd him with all the Joy and Satisfaction that Friendſhip, Love, or Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude could move; here all thoſe nice Pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctilio's that Emulation, Love, or Honour could inſpire, did paſs between theſe Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, Noble Souls: Thus linkt in one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Arms with ſtrict Embraces, they there confirm'd an everlaſting Friendſhip.</p>
                        <p>This Tranſport being over, <hi>Alcidas</hi> by the Company was preſt to tell the Story of his ſtrange Eſcape; who (after ſome Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to the Preſence, and a particular Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs to <hi>Canace,</hi> whom he intreated for a Reconciliation) he gratify'd with this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation:</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="history">
                        <head>The Hiſtory of <hi>Alcidas.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>AFter the fatal Blow I receiv'd under <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace</hi>'s Window, by the Deluge of Blood that per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ued it, I was ſoon diſabled from making any defence, but fell on the Spot,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:151240:67"/>and lay groveling in my Gore: I had juſt ſence enough left to hear the unhappy Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor lament my Fall, who ſoon after retir'd, leaving me for Dead. The Corigidore and his Son going their Rounds, perceived the Body, which knowing, and finding that I yet breath'd, out of Care for my Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, convey'd me to his own Houſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out raiſing an Alarm, which would have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up too much time; they ſtop'd my Blood, and I (after ſome other Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) recover'd my Senſes, and immediately demanded, If they had ſecured any Body upon ſuſpicion; they anſwer'd, <hi>None;</hi> but excus'd that Neglect from their Induſtry to preſerve my Life; I eaſily forgave them, and having underſtood that none knew of my Misfortune but themſelves; I Brib'd them to Secreſie, deſiring to continue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd in their Houſe, till I ſaw what this unlucky Accident would produce, promiſing, if I was likely to Die, to diſcover as much as ſhould take the Guilt off them; and if I liv'd to advance their Fortunes: They had formerly been Servants to my Family, and knew my Capacity of performing what I promiſed: Upon this Score (tho under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of a powerful Aſcendant I had over them) they ſwore a ſolemn Secrecy to my Commands, and likewiſe procur'd me a Chirurgeon, Skilful and very Faithful; thus I remain'd ſecure from ſuſpicion in their
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:151240:68"/>Houſe; and was carefully conceal'd, during the publick Search: After which, happily recovering (tho not without great difficulty) my Eyes were open to the Follies of the World; I abhor'd my extravagant Paſſion, looking upon it as a vaſt Crime, being a Breach of our moſt ſacred and ſolemn Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and the fatal Cauſe of thoſe many Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles that enſued. This moral Reflection wrought ſo effectually with me, that from that moment I reſolved to quit the Vanity of this World, and dedicate all my Love to Heaven, and the Remainder of my Days to the Expiation of my pondrous Sins; 'twas ſome Pleaſure to me alſo when I reflected what a hearty Attonement this would prove for the Wrongs and Injuries I had done to my dear <hi>Octavio.</hi> I defer'd the Execution of my Vow ſome time, leaſt ſome unhappy Wretch might ſuffer for my Death, were not I there to clear him; but all proſpect of a Diſcovery being over, and the Unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate <hi>Alcidas</hi> almoſt forgot, I found it a convenient time to Tranſport my ſelf to <hi>Portugal,</hi> where I entred my ſelf in a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent of <hi>Franciſcans,</hi> and in due time took the Habit and Order. Having left a Charge with the Corigidore not to reveal any know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of me without my Order, unleſs the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of any Man's Life requir'd the Diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which Commands I find he has been very punctual in obſerving. And thus you have
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:151240:68"/>heard the Fate of <hi>Alcidas,</hi> whom Heaven miraculouſly has preſerv'd; no more to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe between your Joys, or be a Plague to any of your Hopes, but plac'd in a Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, luckily to reconcile all Differences, to unite mutual Love, and cement your reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procal Contracts for ever.</p>
                        <p>The Affability, Bravery, and Zeal wherewith <hi>Alcidas</hi> deliver'd this Diſcourſe, and the Pleaſure he ſhew'd, in hopes to be (after all the Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes he had caus'd) the happy Inſtrument to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile them, mov'd every Heart with an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary ſence of his Merit, and from the ſincere Dictates of Love and Eſteem, each addreſs'd him a particular Congratulation; their Joy was unli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited, and there required no Perſwaſions to make an unanimous, Aſſent to gratifie their Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereſt Wiſhes; the fierce Sallies of our Heroes youthful Bloods could hardly be reſtrained within Bounds, nor could the ſubtileſt Artifice conceal the Ladies Tranſports, whilſt their becoming Bluſhes betray'd their Thoughts, and their dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Eyes diſcover'd their Impatience for the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching Happineſs; nothing but the Viſcount's Illneſs was an Obſtacle to their Bliſs, for whoſe Recovery they waited; but he, the only Unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate, having had the Pleaſure of hearing this Relation, and the boundleſs Joy of once again ſeeing and receiving to his Boſome his dear <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace,</hi> on whom he confer'd ten thouſand Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings; he had the Satisfaction to depart this Life in Peace, loaden with Honour, and with Years, leaving <hi>Frederick</hi> and ſhe, the happy Poſſeſſors of a vaſt Inheritance.</p>
                        <p>Sorrow for this Loſs had ſomething eclipſed the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:151240:69"/>Tranquility of every Breaſt, and defer'd their Joys, to pay a mournful Tribute to the bleſt Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of the Noble Deceas'd, living in as much Comfort as the occaſion would permit, till a juſt time was expired for their Grief, when they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to enter the Liſts of Matrimony, and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian</hi> perform'd the Nuptial-Rites.</p>
                        <q>
                           <lg n="1">
                              <head>I.</head>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Now does each Bridegroom's Face appear</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>In Joy, which their warm Hearts expreſs,</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Waiting for That they purchas'd dear,</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>And Sighing, Languiſh to poſſeſs.</hi>
                              </l>
                           </lg>
                           <lg n="2">
                              <head>II.</head>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>The trembling Brides with wiſhing Eyes,</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>By equal Love and Tears opprest,</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Long to ſecure the Noble Prize,</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>But dare not, dare not think the rest.</hi>
                              </l>
                           </lg>
                           <lg n="3">
                              <head>III.</head>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Thus to Compoſe the cruel Pain,</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>That Dying Lovers oft endure,</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>When all Endeavour is in vain,</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>Hymen <hi>effects the mighty Cure.</hi>
                              </l>
                           </lg>
                        </q>
                        <p>The Ceremony was very magnificent, and at Bed-time <hi>Adrian</hi> confeſs'd, That his Soul was ſo abſolutely reſign'd to Heaven, that he could ſee his Miſtreſs in the Arms of his Friend without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret. Where we will leave both Couple, 'tis poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, to Repoſe.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Curtains drawn, the rest must not be known,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Inquire no more, the time may be your own.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
